<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The peasants price of spirituall liberty. VVherein is represented the complexion of the times, and considerations to cure it. In three sermons. By Nathaniel Homes, D.D.</title>
            <author>Homes, Nathanael, 1599-1678.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 151 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86502</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2571</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E151_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15127</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859803</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859803</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111902</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86502)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111902)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 27:E151[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The peasants price of spirituall liberty. VVherein is represented the complexion of the times, and considerations to cure it. In three sermons. By Nathaniel Homes, D.D.</title>
                  <author>Homes, Nathanael, 1599-1678.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 77, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.O. and G.D. for Benjamin Allen in Popeshead Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title page has printer's device (McK. 290).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Freedom of religion --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111902:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:111902:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PEASANTS PRICE OF SPIRITVALL LIBERTY. VVherein is repreſented the <hi>Complexion</hi> of the <hi>Times,</hi> and <hi>Conſiderations</hi> to Cure it. In three <hi>Sermons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Nathaniel Homes,</hi> D.D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. O.</hi> and <hi>G. D.</hi> for <hi>Benjamin Allen</hi> in <hi>Popeſhead Alley,</hi> 1642.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:111902:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:111902:2"/>
            <head>THE PEASANTS PRICE <hi>Of Spirituall</hi> LIBERTY.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Chron. 4. Verſ. 21.22.23.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">I begin ſo high as the 21. verſe, and take in all three Verſes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they make up one diſtinct compleat Table of the Genealo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie of <hi>Shelah,</hi> the third Sonne of <hi>Iudah, Gen.</hi> 38. And in ſome Greek copies the 4. chap. begins at verſ. 21.</note> 
                     <hi>21.</hi> The Sons of <hi>Shelah,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Iudah,</hi> were <hi>Er,</hi> the Father of <hi>Lecah,</hi> and <hi>Laadah</hi> the Father of <hi>Mareſha,</hi> and the families of the houſe of them that wrought fine linnen, of the houſe of <hi>Aſhbea.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>22.</hi> And <hi>Iokim,</hi> and the men of <hi>Chozebah,</hi> and <hi>loaſh,</hi> and <hi>Saraph,</hi> who had dominion in <hi>Moab,</hi> and <hi>Iaſhubi-Lehem.</hi> And theſe are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient things.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>23.</hi> Theſe were the Potters, and thoſe that dwelt among Plants and Hedges. There they dwelt with the King for his worke.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe Books of <hi>Chronicles,</hi> are in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> calle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Bookes of dayes,</hi> i. e. of times, becauſe they more exactly ſet downe the times of the reignes of the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Anſwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>able to the ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of the Hebr we call them <hi>Chronicles.</hi>
               </note> and of the tributaries and captivities of the State. The <hi>Greek</hi> (the Sept.) call them B <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111902:3"/>i. e. <hi>Books of things omitted.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">For <hi>Chron.</hi> goes as low in repetition as as 1 <hi>Sam</hi> 27. compare 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.</note> Becauſe what the Holy Ghoſt of purpoſe paſſed over in the Books of <hi>Samuel</hi> &amp; <hi>Kings,</hi> it reſerved &amp; poſted over as more proper and pertinent to the Books of <hi>Chronicles</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Of whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h Bookes of Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles, that long ſince periſhed, theſe Books of Chroni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>les out of whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h I take this Text are a divine, authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick epitome. <hi>Pellic. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſted.</hi>
               </note> And among the things omitted in <hi>Samuel</hi> and <hi>Kings,</hi> theſe Genealogies are here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, as the foundation of all compleat hiſtory.</p>
            <p>The order of theſe Genealogies runs up to the head, begins at the beginning both of the world and the Word, <hi>viz. Adam,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron. Chap.</hi> 1. And by that time it comes to this <hi>Chapter,</hi> it is come to the poſterity of <hi>Juda,</hi> one of the twelve <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs,</hi> borne of <hi>Iacob;</hi> and by the 21. <hi>verſe</hi> of this <hi>Chapter,</hi> it is run downe as low as the third ſonne of <hi>Judah:</hi> namely, <hi>Shelah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And the ſonnes of</hi> Shelah, <hi>the ſonne of</hi> Judah, <hi>were</hi> Er, <hi>the Father of, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To tell you what is in my Text, before I open it, were to bid you looke into a boxe of Jewels, whiles I hold downe the cover.</p>
            <p>Give me leave for the opening of it, to goe my owne way (as God diſpenſeth to his Miniſters ſeverall gifts, all for edification) that I may ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie my ſelfe and you:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Grammatically,</hi> theſe things neceſſarily are to be obſerved.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That there ſhould be a fuller ſtop, or point in our Engliſh at <hi>Mareſha,</hi> then the <hi>Comma</hi> ['] For it is in the Hebrew [^] <hi>Athnach,</hi> which anſwers to our Engliſh [:] <hi>Colon,</hi> which pointing (if obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in our Engliſh) would more explaine the true reading, thus: That as <hi>Shelah</hi> was the ſonne of <hi>Iudah;</hi> ſo the ſonnes of <hi>Shelah</hi> were firſt <hi>Er,</hi> the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111902:3"/>father of <hi>Lecah:</hi> ſecondly, <hi>Laadah</hi> the father of <hi>Mareſha.</hi> And thirdly, the family of the houſe of <hi>Aſhbea,</hi> that wrought fine linnen; and not that <hi>Laadah</hi> was the father of <hi>Mareſha,</hi> and of thoſe of the houſe of <hi>Aſhbea</hi> too; as at firſt ſight, by the Engliſh pointing, or ſtop, it may ſeeme.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thing obſervable in the <hi>Grammar</hi> of the Text is; <note place="margin">So in the Heb. They were the Families of the houſe of the work of Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen Cloth, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> byſſini operis.</note> that the families of the houſe of <hi>Aſhbea</hi> are ſaid to <hi>worke</hi> or to <hi>have wrought fine linnen,</hi> i. e. <hi>made linnen cloth.</hi> They were Cloth-workers or makers of linnen cloth, not workers in linnen cloth; as may be ſaid of <hi>Seamſters</hi> or <hi>Embroderers.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>the men of</hi> Chozeba may be rendred: <hi>The men of a Ly</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">So <hi>Pellican.</hi> So old <hi>Lát. Viri mendacii.</hi> 1</note> or of <hi>lying,</hi> or <hi>deceipt,</hi> or <hi>deceiving.</hi> And this is expreſt in a <hi>Chaldean</hi> dialect:<note place="margin">For <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies a ly, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though here it be admitted, that <hi>Chozeba</hi> be a proper name; yet queſtionleſſe ſome <hi>ly</hi> in words,<note place="margin">Note that herein the text ſoundeth of <hi>Babylon.</hi> For <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>haldai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in being written <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> or in workes; ſome telling, or (as <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.15.) making a <hi>ly</hi> became ominous, and at firſt gave the name of the place. For places of themſelves are not named; and after that, here the place gives name to the men that dwelt-there.</p>
            <p>There is yet one thing more to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the <hi>Grammar</hi> of the words, <hi>viz.</hi> Whether wee are to underſtand in the Text, <hi>Hedges,</hi> or <hi>Walls;</hi> and conſequently, whether <hi>Hedgers</hi> or <hi>Maiſons:</hi> For their dwelling, <hi>viz. among plants, &amp;c.</hi> notes their occupation, as wee ſhall touch more in the laying open of the parts of the Text. The queſtion is occaſioned, becauſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies a fence, whether of an <hi>Hedge</hi> or a <hi>Wall;</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially a wall of meere ſtone without morter.</p>
            <p>Our reſolution is, that no doubt, <hi>Hedgers</hi> muſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111902:4"/>be implyed in the Text, becauſe they had fences about their plants; and it is not likely they were all of ſtone walls; yea, to make quick-ſet hedges, is a part of planting, and very probably here ſuppoſed, elſe how ſhould the King have ſo much imployment for ſo many, for ſo many yeeres? But for the particular word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in expreſſe termes, it is more like that this <hi>Gederah</hi> is to be rendred <hi>wall,</hi> and ſo ſignifies the men were <hi>Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</hi> Thus <hi>Rabbi Salomon Iarchi</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">On the text on the word <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran,</hi> a <hi>fence;</hi> or as was he erendred, <hi>hedges.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>i. e.</hi> Fence they were Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tects, or Maſons, or makers of Wall, namely of Stone wall, for the buſineſſe of the King.</note> abſolutely af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes, a man in a point of this nature to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, it being touching the acceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a word of their owne naturall language, <hi>i. e</hi> the <hi>Hebrew.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Holy Ghoſt neceſſitateth me to touch upon the <hi>Rhetoricke</hi> of the Text; or elſe I cannot make you underſtand the Text: as after the ſhuts of a window of an houſe are taken downe, things in the houſe are diſcerned, by their colours. The maine thing in this way to be noted, is a <hi>Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall prolepſis, pre-occupation</hi> or <hi>anticipation;</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Holy Ghoſt ſpeakes of that now, which long after was done in order of time. For the <hi>Iewes</hi> here genealogized were not in captivity, till the laſt Chapter of the 2. of <hi>Chron.</hi> yet here is mention of certaine that carried in <hi>Babylon,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they had freedome granted to return, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, theſe <hi>Potters, &amp;c.</hi> This way of ſetting downe things wee call <hi>anticipation,</hi> or <hi>prevention.</hi> That theſe generations now ſet downe before the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of King <hi>David</hi> (who was foureteene gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations before the captivity) are noted to ſtay in the place of that <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> captivity,<note place="margin">Math 1.17.</note> after the ſeventy yeeres captivity were ended.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:111902:4"/>
            <p>And this <hi>anticipation</hi> is manifeſt, 1. By con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering who is deemed to be the Pen-man of this Booke of <hi>Chronicles,</hi> viz. <hi>Ezra,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">So <hi>Vatablus Pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licanus, Innius. in Tit. prior<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> libr. Chronicorum.</hi> And ſo the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews themſelvs. who doe therfore put the Books of <hi>Chron.</hi> after the Book of <hi>Ezra.</hi> They collect that <hi>Ezra</hi> penned the <hi>Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on.</hi> By that in the end of the ſaid Book. For both but one Book in the Heb.</note> viz. <hi>Ezra,</hi> who was a principall man of them that returned out of captivity. 2. By conſidering, that although the ten Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> are here reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as they were leſt recorded in the greater Chronicles before the captivity: (For they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver returned to bring a copy with them) yet <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> is reckoned after the Records brought out of captivity, as the<note n="*" place="margin">See before p. 3. marg. And ſee af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter p 7. in marg.</note> 
               <hi>Chaldean</hi> dialect witneſſeth. And ſo <hi>Ezra</hi> in the compiling of theſe epito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Chronicles, doth recite ſome paſſages of them in <hi>Babylon,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">For this ſenerall re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>koning of their ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ealogies let the learned remember the Hebr. Accents, 1 Chron. chap. 9. v. 1. comparing <hi>Nehem.</hi> 7.6 <hi>Ezra</hi> 2.1. whereupon <hi>Innius</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ds thus. <hi>Et om<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> guidem Iſraeli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ae ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nſits ſunt, uteree ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ript: ſunt in lib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum Iſraeli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. I chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> vero ut cum deportati ſunt in Babilomam prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter praevari cat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</hi>
               </note> as he goes: and this <hi>anticipation</hi> is common in all Hiſtories, both Divine and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, to the end that things may be diſpatched at once as they goe, and prevent needleſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, for the <hi>Theologicall</hi> conſideration of the Text, to find out the Divinity that lies in it; the golden Key to open it, is, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36. verſ. <hi>ult. Thus ſaith</hi> Cyrus, <hi>King of</hi> Perſia; <hi>All the kingdomes of the earth hath the Lord God of Heaven given mee, and he hath charged me to build him an houſe in</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, <hi>which is in</hi> Judah, <hi>who is there among you of all his people? the Lord his God be with him, and let him goe up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The wards filed in this golden Key, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing may let or hinder the unlocking of their liberty, are deſcribed, <hi>Ezra</hi> 6.8.9, &amp;c. <hi>More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over</hi> (ſaith the King of <hi>Babylon</hi>) <hi>I make a decree, what yee ſhall doe to the Elders of the</hi> Jewes, <hi>for the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111902:5"/>building of this houſe of God; that of the Kings goods even of the tribute beyond the river, forthwith expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces be given unto theſe men, that they be not hindred; and that which they have need of, both young Bullocks and Rams, and Lambs for the burnt offerings of the God of Heaven, Wheat, Salt, Wine, and Oyle, according to the appointment of the Prieſts which are at</hi> Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, <hi>let it be given them, day by day, without faile. That they may offer ſacrifices of ſweet ſavour unto the God of heaven, and pray for the life of the King, and of his ſonnes. Alſo I have made a decree, that whoſoever ſhall alter this word, let timber be pulled down from his houſe, and being ſet up, let him be hanged thereupon, and let his houſe be made a dung hill for this. And the God that hath cauſed his name to dwell there, deſtroy all Kings and people that ſhall put to their hand, to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and deſtroy this houſe of God, which is at</hi> Ieruſalem. <hi>I</hi> Darius <hi>have made a decree, let it be done.</hi> Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this Key, and theſe wards, yet the bolt on theſe mens hearts in the Text, their ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did obſtinate ſpirit will not turne, they will not returne, but as if it were hereditary to them to live among Heathens, they will tarry in <hi>Babylon.</hi> I ſay <hi>ſordid</hi> and <hi>hereditary;</hi> becauſe the more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured of their ſtocke were onely ſuch as had<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> They ruled in <hi>Moab, prorage.</hi> to <hi>Iun.</hi> Therfore the Septuagint read it only <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſome under-rule, and inferiour authority com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to them, made Deputies. And that au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority they had, was in Heatheniſh <hi>Moab,</hi> and it is not altogether improbable, that they might at their firſt comming into <hi>Iudea</hi> be (by the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſide at leaſt) <hi>Moabites;</hi> having their firſt deſcent and originall from<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ruth</hi> 1. v. 1. compare v. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Ruth</hi> the <hi>Moabitiſh,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111902:5"/>Ruth Chap.</hi> 1. For <hi>Jaſhubi. Lehem</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">The Heb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which words with a ſmall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a lectiene</hi> (put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) common in Heb Bib. may be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> And the Heb Bi. magn. with the Major. writ, with (o) over it, as a note of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective writing, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> was put for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> And Rab. Shol. Iarch. puts <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the middle, as of the root, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>REVERTERE.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> by a Chaldean tang, or dialect of ſhort ſpeaking, for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> As in the Goſpel, according to the Syria k which is in a manner Chalde) <hi>Lazar</hi> for <hi>Eleazar</hi> Luk 16. Or the name <hi>Lechem,</hi> barely without the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of <hi>Beth,</hi> i. e. the houſe of <hi>Lechem.</hi> For this reading, See Pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic. &amp; Bib. Graec. Complut. which render thus, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. So old <hi>Lat</hi> Some read them, <hi>Habitatores Lechem. Pagn.</hi> As if <hi>Iaſhub:</hi> were of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Arias.</hi> So that learned pious Italian proteſtant Commentator Bruccioli <hi>Et gli. Habitatori di lehem.</hi>
               </note> with very little change, even of one letter, and with no vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence to the Text may be rendered, <hi>They that returned from</hi> Moab <hi>to</hi> Lehem. <hi>i. e.</hi> Bethlehem. And ſo long had theſe contemners of libertie ſettled in <hi>Babylon,</hi> that all their former conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, more or leſſe, better or worſe, either by their linſey woolſey habitation in <hi>Moab,</hi> or by their linnen web in the houſe of <hi>Aſhbea,</hi> is worne out, through the antiquitie of their laſt and worſt condition. <hi>Theſe are</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>antient things.</hi> Their linnen cloth weaving or working is now become to be in the memory of man as old rotten ragges. Their <hi>Moabitiſh</hi> honour is become obſolet. So many, many yeeres ſince, have they made morter, twirled the Potters wheele<note n="(a)" place="margin">As the men of <hi>China.</hi> The next generation only living to ſee the pots made by the former.</note>; ſowne <hi>Cucumbers,</hi> hedged and ditched: ſo that now all former civill indifferent conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is drowned and buried in dirt, and dunghil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardens; and that for the <hi>Kings</hi> worke <hi>there,</hi> i. e. The <hi>King of Babylon,</hi> 
               <note n="[b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iun.</hi> in verſ. 22. in verſ. 23. <hi>in Tabul</hi> 4. <hi>Dyke</hi> in a Sermon on 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.21. The 72. Greek Tranſlators alſo thus un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the Text in all probability. And they were learned Iewes. For thus they tranſlate. The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e they abode, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. i. e. They not lonely abode there, but were comforted there, or eſtabliſhed there in their worke, which had been no wonder of <hi>Iudea,</hi> but ſpoken as a remarkable paſſage, muſt be meant of <hi>Babylon.</hi>
               </note> an <hi>Heathen King,</hi> that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then King that had captivated them, and he that had done it once before to the ten Tribes, That Heathen King of <hi>Babylon</hi> they ſerve in'very mean imployments. To averre this interpretation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide that which hath beene already touched, that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111902:6"/>
               <hi>Ezra</hi> (one of the returned captives from <hi>Babylon</hi>) is the Penman: That the Text hath in it touches of the <hi>Chaldean</hi> Dialect, where they were capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated; and that the Genealogies are reckoned up in relation to their captivity: I ſay, beſide thoſe things, much more (if meete for a Sermon) might be ſaid. But to ſay in a word what wee ſhall ſay.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>This aboad there with the King for his worke</hi> cannot be meant of <hi>Moab:</hi> for to ſay that they had dominion in <hi>Moab,</hi> and yet they were Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in <hi>Moab,</hi> were an unlikely thing, if not a contradiction. The period of their <hi>Moabitiſh</hi> condition was <hi>Jaſhubi-Lechem;</hi> they returned to <hi>Lechem,</hi> not to <hi>Babylon;</hi> but many yeeres after, yea, many generations after, they were carryed (not went of themſelves, much leſſe <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned</hi>) unto <hi>Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>This abode there with</hi> the King for his worke, cannot be meant of <hi>Iudea,</hi> with King <hi>David,</hi> as the <hi>Geneva</hi> notes expreſſe. For then the Holy Ghoſt would not have cloſed at <hi>Jaſhubi-Lechem,</hi> that thoſe aforeſaid things onely were ancient things: but would have firſt taken in this note of their Potter-trade, &amp;c. and then have conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; theſe are ancient things. For King <hi>Davids</hi> time, in compariſon of their returne from cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity was ancient, <hi>viz.</hi> threeſcore and ten yeers above foureteene generations and upwards: ſo that any man may eaſily perceive that the Holy Ghoſt puts a cleare <hi>Antitheſis,</hi> or flat oppoſition of diſtinction between theſe two. Firſt, the ſons of <hi>Selah</hi> wrought fine linnen, and had ſome rule
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111902:6"/>in <hi>Moab,</hi> and after returned to <hi>Lechem.</hi> And theſe are antient things. But their being Potters, &amp;c. theſe in compariſon of thoſe, are moderne and late, eſpecially their continuing in that conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to this day.</p>
            <p>Therefore theſe words, <hi>There they abode with the King for his worke,</hi> muſt be meant of the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> in <hi>Babylon.</hi> To which purpoſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne not the obſervation of the Tenſe or Time the Holy Ghoſt uſeth in expreſſing their <hi>habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> or <hi>dwelling. viz</hi> Firſt, the <hi>Preſent Tenſe,</hi> or <hi>Time</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Hebr. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Benoni Pag. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitantes. So the Septuagint, and without a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. So Iun. and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an &amp; <hi>Iſtiſunt figuli illi, deſiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ad</hi> &amp;c. So old Lat. <hi>Hi ſunt figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li habitantes.</hi> So Vatabl. <hi>Iſti ſunt figuli illi habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantes.</hi>
               </note>. There they <hi>doe</hi> dwell: as if he ſhould ſay, there they <hi>doe now dwell</hi> to this day. And then after the <hi>paſt time;</hi> there they <hi>have dwelt. i. e.</hi> A long time they have dwelt, where they now dwell. And ſurely it had beene a ſtrange thing for an Hiſtorian to tell us of that which was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily to be ſuppoſed. That anciently in King <hi>Davids</hi> time theſe dwelt <hi>there,</hi> i. e. in <hi>Judea</hi> with King <hi>David</hi> for his worke: why, where ſhould they dwell elſe, whiles in his worke? Nor can it be likely, but that men of other tribes might be King <hi>Davids</hi> Potters (if <hi>David</hi> had any) and would have beene as ſoone mentioned, as thoſe of the ſame royall Tribe, of which King <hi>David</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe was; if the ſtory of <hi>Davids</hi> time had beene here intended (mentioned no where elſe.) Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Ioſephus</hi> in his <hi>Antiquities</hi> affirmeth, that ſome,<note place="margin">Lib. Antiq. 11. cap. 1. Edit. Aug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> when this liberty of returning out of <hi>Babylon</hi> was offered, refuſed to returne.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee I build upon Reaſon, not upon bare Authority of learned mens judgements (which is not my way) Not that I am alone in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111902:7"/>this ſenſe of my Text. I have before noted, that the <hi>Septuagint. Iunius,</hi> and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>I. Dyke</hi> ſo take this Text, and ſo do divers others; and that not only in their tranſlations in the languages of the Schooles, but alſo in the languages of Nations.<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Daſe. bet.</hi> Nemlech in Babylonien.</note> 
               <hi>Piſcator</hi> in his high-Dutch Bible tranſlates it, v. 22. emphatically <hi>there;</hi> and then in his Notes ſaith, <hi>Namely in Babylon:</hi> So<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Di mora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> quivi apreſſo de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re per far<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>l lave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro di eſſo.</hi> Secon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do alcum in Babilonia done eferci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>avano que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ſeaz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> curarſi di <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare al lore parſs.</note> 
               <hi>Deodat</hi> in his <hi>Italian</hi> Bible, <hi>there</hi> they abode, &amp;c. That is, (ſaith hee) according to ſome, <hi>They abode in</hi> Babylon, where they exerciſed thoſe trades without any care to returne to their owne Countrey.</p>
            <p>And thus all <hi>Shelah</hi> his poſterity was meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morphoſed into dirt; from the Loome they ſell into the Lome; from their <hi>Moabitiſh</hi> honour, they fall into <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> mire.</p>
            <p>In the words thus opened,
<list>
                  <item>Obſerve 1. The <hi>Matter.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Obſerve 2. The <hi>Forme.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Matter</hi> is the <hi>men</hi> mentioned.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Forme</hi> is the phraſe and ſcope of the <hi>Pen</hi> mentioning.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Matter</hi> containes,
<list>
                  <item>1. The generation.</item>
                  <item>2. The degeneration.</item>
               </list>
Of the ſonnes of <hi>Shelah,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Iudah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Generation,</hi> or, firſt or better Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them all, or any of them at the beſt, are notable, but Either for their <hi>Practice,</hi> Or their <hi>Place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Practice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt are named <hi>Cloth-workers,</hi> or <hi>Weavers</hi> of Linnen.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:111902:7"/>
            <p>Secondly <hi>Deputies,</hi> Deputie Governours, or <hi>Iudges,</hi> or ſome ſuch inferiour <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> in <hi>Moab;</hi> but ſtill note the phraſe, <hi>in Moab.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Place;</hi> as their <hi>practice</hi> doth not lift them very high, ſo their <hi>place</hi> doth not helpe much af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. They are (as the Proverb is) <hi>but ill holp up:</hi> for they (eſpecially ſome of them) are ſaid to be men of <hi>Chozeba,</hi> i. e. men of <hi>The ly,</hi> probably appliable to all; ſure enough men of <hi>mechanick Art, Handicrafts-men,</hi> have in their callings ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny temptations to <hi>Ly.</hi> And lying and poverty are oft-times companions, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30. And lying is a principall piece of a carnall <hi>Politician;</hi> his <hi>Maxime</hi> being that:</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qui neſcit diſsimulare, neſcit vivere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He that cannot lye, cannot live.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Or, if wee take the place as a <hi>proper name,</hi> not as a common terme, yet ſtill the place is rather a meanneſſe than a mainneſſe of commendation; ſo that if wee doe not call them the men of the <hi>Ly,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Le, Ley</hi> or <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eigh.</hi> But. ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies a place, or. Paſture, Camd. Remai.</note> but men of the <hi>Le</hi> (a name of many places in <hi>England</hi>) yet ſo meane a place was this <hi>Le,</hi> or <hi>Chozeba,</hi> that it is never more mentioned in the Scripture that I can finde.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Degeneration,</hi> They in ſuccceding ages much degenerate from that their anceſtors were; of which you heard but juſt now; and fall downe to a very meane condition, from cloth to the clay, from ruling to reeling, or turning the <hi>Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> wheele.</p>
            <p>Diſtinctly their degenerating is ſet forth:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111902:8"/>
               <list>
                  <item>1. By their <hi>practice.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. By their <hi>place.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. By their <hi>project.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. By the <hi>prorogation</hi> of all:</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>Practice</hi> or <hi>Calling.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <note place="margin">For the places of them habitation intimates their imployment. So Rab. S Iarch. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> (I need not co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tranſlate any further, you hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heard of their walling afore. p. 4. marg.) <hi>i. e. Theſe were potters or faſhioners of ſome or clay for the buſineſſe of the King. And alſo belonging to the ſordid or drud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery imployment of the King, and the Princes. Thoſe dwellers among plants, were thoſe that were imployed in the plantations of the King.</hi>
                  </note> 1. Dirty <hi>Potters.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. Dunghill <hi>Planters.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. Duſty <hi>Wallers.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>I ſet them forth thus; not but that the callings are to be reſpected; but their preferring theſe before liberty, is to be diſgraced according to the intent of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Place.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>With the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Babylon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Yea, in <hi>Babylon;</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Yea, <hi>Labouring there;</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Yea, moſt <hi>ſordid works</hi> there, in the mire.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Merchandiſing may tranſport a man beyond the Sea, yet not alwayes to Heathen <hi>Kingdomes;</hi> if to a heathen <hi>Kingdome,</hi> not to the <hi>worke,</hi> or to any relation to, or dependance on a <hi>King,</hi> oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to true <hi>Religion;</hi> if ſo, yet not in buſineſſes of the moſt ſordid nature. But theſe deſcend to the loweſt ſtep of baſeneſſe of ſpirit; and that with all aggravations, chooſing and preferring rather to be the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Babylons</hi> dirty day-labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, then to enjoy their civill liberty of body and ſtate; and their ſpirituall liberty of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of ſoule: Neither longing after their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſoyle, nor liſtening after their ſpirituall Temple; nor hoaning after their kindred and nation in the fleſh, nor harkning after the Prieſts and Prophets indued with the ſpirit. In a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:111902:8"/>word; nor the good of <hi>Iudeah,</hi> nor the bad of <hi>Babylon</hi> can make them deſire a change of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, though to the better.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Project.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All theſe meane imployments in this meane place, are by them <hi>projected</hi> and choſen;</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Voluntarily,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sordidly.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Voluntarily;</hi> this is ſtrongly touched in the word <hi>dwell:</hi> for, though for ſeventy yeeres they were carryed away captive: ſo 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36. and ſeventy yeeres captivity were to be fulfilled (as <hi>Ierem.</hi> and <hi>Dan.</hi> propheſied) yet now they are <hi>inhabitants,</hi> and there they <hi>dwell.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">For both theſe n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed of theſe potters <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and alſo <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> They tooke houſes, leaſes, or purchaſed: they might, and ſhould (but would not) goe up; they accepted not of liberty.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Sordidly,</hi> The beſt of the <hi>project</hi> could be but for worke; and a meane worke too, neither handſome nor wholeſome. To tread clay, dwell in poore Cottages; ſee what ropes of ſand, what cords of graſſe draw carnall men from ſalvation, both of body and ſoule. Was there no worke in <hi>Iudeah</hi> to be had, that might intice them thither?</p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>Prorogation,</hi> the time they had thus degenerated; had uſed theſe poore plots and meanes for a maintenance, ſet forth in three degrees.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Dwelling,</hi> which is more then <hi>ſojourning.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. Dwelt <hi>with the King;</hi> therefore more then ſeventy yeeres there: for ſeventy yeeres they had been captivated there.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>Theſe are ancient things:</hi> they ſo long
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111902:9"/>had degenerated, and uſed theſe meane imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that all things preceding <hi>theſe</hi> imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are very ancient and obſolet, ſo as not to be mentioned ſcarcely.</item>
            </list>
            <p>So that this cuſtome of their <hi>ſordid</hi> imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment preſcribed againſt imitation of any better things imitable in their anceſtors.</p>
            <p>Thus of the Matter of the Text.</p>
            <p>Next of the Forme or Manner, uſed by the Penman. <hi>Ezra,</hi> out of all doubt (with all mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty to dive into the ſcope) ſets downe theſe things, at leaſt ſome of them by way, of diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the men here mentioned.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe ſpeaking the beſt of them, he puts it off; <hi>But thoſe are ancient things:</hi> as if not to be looked at in their behalfe that had ſo imbaſed themſelves: As a naturall man in his naturall Dialect or Phraſe of ſpeech would ſay:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Etgenus, &amp; proavos, &amp; quae nonfecimus ipſi,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vix ea noſtro voco—</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe <hi>Ezra</hi> tells every circumſtance of their baſeneſſe of ſpirit, without any mitigation, or helping the matter afterwards, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In what place of the land?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Among Plants and Hedges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what was the cauſe?</p>
            <p>Even for worke, for no better, or greater preferment.</p>
            <p>Lay all theſe together, and they will compoſe this one point.</p>
            <p>The Lord records with diſgrace, and diſcards as graceleſſe men of ſuch unworthy ſpirits, who preſcribe antiquity to preferre a ſordid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111902:9"/>before a God-given libertie.</p>
            <p>The <hi>illation</hi> or deduction of this point is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent: For it containes, or is made up of all the limbs, joynts and parts of the Text. So that take the Doctrine aſunder, and preſently it is reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into all the parts.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>explication</hi> of the point, let us goe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the order of the nature of things in the Doctrine. And ſo to reſolve every <hi>Quaere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Q. <hi>What is a God-given liberty?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſ.</hi> I call it ſo, becauſe it proceedeth from Gods gift by proclamation, and containes two liberties: firſt, Perſonall; of body, ſtate and condition: ſecondly, Spirituall, of ſoule and worſhip. See <hi>Ezra,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Chap 1, v, 1, 2, 3.</note> the King proclaimes not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly liberty for them to goe up from <hi>Babylon,</hi> but alſo to build Gods houſe at <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All theſe put together, are a right platforme of Chriſtians purchaſed liberty, <hi>viz.</hi> The par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition wall is downe; all are ſubjects to Chriſts Kingdome; all brethren; no longer ſlaves, ſo much as <hi>civilly.</hi> And <hi>Eccleſiaſtically;</hi> all needleſſe Ceremonies<note n="*" place="margin">Some derive the word <hi>Ceremonie, à Ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tibis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> a people of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trutia that care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully obſerved the Heatheniſh Superſtitions of the veſtall Nuns belonging to Veſta, when Heathen <hi>Rome</hi> was taken of the Galli. To whom I thus farre aſſent, that Abundance of the Ceremonies now in uſe in Chriſtendome, are Heatheniſh in their forme, and alſo in their originall; as may be ſeen at full in <hi>Papatus ſeu Depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate religionis origine et incremento, per Thom. Mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſinum.</hi> Others derive Ceremon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea <hi>Carends,</hi> To which <hi>Etymon</hi> I muſt needs aſſent: For even the Iewiſh Ceremonies intimated a want or abſence of the Antitype, as not yet come in the fleſh: But I think not unfitly are they derived of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> time, or occaſion, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to abide. Becauſe they were to indure, the beſt of them at moſt but for a time.</note> ſuperſtitions and humane inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are put dawne. And ſo <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are no longer ſubject to <hi>thoſe rudiments of the world,</hi> of which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2. longer to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111902:10"/>live in ſubjection to ſuch ordinances as theſe, <hi>Tou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h not, taſte not, handle not; after the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and doctrines of men, which things have a ſhew of humility in will-worſhip and neglect of the body.</hi> For (ſaith he) <hi>yee a e com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leat in him,</hi> i. e in Chriſt, both for ſalvation<note n="*" place="margin">Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> penul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>, as alſo for matter and form of worſhip, doctrine and diſcipline<note n="(a)" place="margin">Heb. 3.6 7.</note>; and therefore in all to heare his voyce<note n="(b)" place="margin">Heb. 5. v. 2.</note> laſtly, <hi>ſpiritually</hi> ſin is put downe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6 2.14.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Q <hi>What is that ſordid condition which ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre in oppoſition to a God-given liberty?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>R.</hi> Theſe in the Text preferre firſt ſordidneſſe in civill things; if they could, as yet to this day weave, or ſpin linnen, it ſeemes by all circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances they would rather doe it for the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> then for the Temple; If they had yet left in them any ſpirit of government or rule; they would ſooner exerciſe it in a <hi>Moab</hi> an <hi>Heathen</hi> Kingdome then in <hi>Iudeah.</hi> It is an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to a civill Art, if it workes for ſome great perſonage, King or Prince, or for ſome great project,<note place="margin">Exod. 31. v. 1. to v. 7.</note> ſome ſtate deſigne. But theſe men are farre from this; yea, farre more ſordid in civill things then this; They imbrace the dirt-dau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing condition of Potters, &amp;c. they ſubject themſelves to Heathen Lawes and Commands, and are among Heathen company.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Sordidneſſe in ſpirituall things; to ſee ſo much idolarty, Heatheniſh impiety, &amp;c. The true worſhip of the true God for the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall not here, no ſigne of a Church there: for theſe in the Text ſeeme to be all for the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111902:10"/>King of <hi>Babylons</hi> worke, and they dwelt among Plants, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>All theſe put together, are againe a Platform of imbaſed ſpirits in all ages; that regard not what become of Lawes, Religion, Liberties &amp;c. They are contented to grind at the mill with <hi>Sampſon,</hi> having their eyes put out (they muſt not ſee who hurt them) ſo as they may but live, and have for backe and belly; if they may have their <hi>oves &amp; boves,</hi> their flocks &amp; herds, its no matter to them, if the Church and State be made <hi>Aſſes,</hi> to to beare intollerable burthens; or as it is ſaid in <hi>Iob: The Oxen were plowing,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The Papiſts make this moral. The Oxen ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Clergie, the Aſſes the Laitie. But by the idleneſſe of their Clergie, the Oxen ſhould not fitly ſignifie them</note> 
               <hi>and the Aſſes ſtood feeding by;</hi> ſo the worthyeſt in Church and State are toyled, and the dull worthleſſe <hi>Aſſes</hi> often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times pampered and promoted; but with men of this ſpirit we ſpeake of, it is nothing, if the <hi>Oxen,</hi> the moſt profitableſt pillars of the Church and Common-wealth be yoaked and drawne hard, and gaulled: Such <hi>Aſſes</hi> care not how Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall and Civill liberties be yoaked and ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered, ſo they may ſtand ſtill and feed.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Q. <hi>How doe ſuch imbaſed ſpirits preſcribe and plead antiquity for their evill way, ſo to love a meane condition,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tit 1.12. &amp; Col. 2.</note> 
               <hi>and neglect their libertie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>R.</hi> So as they doe here; having time out of minde beene Potters in <hi>Babylon</hi> (for ſo they had beene above the age of a man:) a better condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of making linnen, or returning to <hi>Lechem,</hi> i.e. <hi>Bethlechem</hi> is too farre out of mind to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded by them. It would, as it were, ſeeme an <hi>Innovation</hi> to change from what they had been. A juſt patterne of later times. Men have beene
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111902:11"/>(a many of them) ſo long in love with <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Poperie</hi> and foppery; with Popiſhneſſe and apiſhneſſe, that to turne to a ſpirituall ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall divinely warranted worſhip, were in their opinion an <hi>Innovation.</hi> And therefore Popiſh ſpirits for all their muſty, <hi>Gibeonitiſh</hi> diſſembled old ſtuffe, either of any unwarrantable ſorts of <hi>Prelatie,</hi> or of an unmeet unworthy Miniſtry, or Popiſh ceremony, or practice of impiety; ſtill, ſtill they cry up antiquity. <q>Plead cuſtome or preſcription; thus it hath beene, ſay they, and thus long it hath beene thus, in the Church. And therefore never to be altered;</q> though it would very eaſily be replyed: have ſuch rags growne old in the Church? <hi>Quo jure,</hi> what equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was there for it? The longer they have been ſuffered in the Church, the ancienter is the ſin. If they have beene ſo old; in all likelihood they are growne rotten and naſty in the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of men, (<hi>emunctae naris,</hi> of acute judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.) And if rotten and naſty, for ſhame why are they not caſt out? If a yard of cloth make an infant a ſufficient coat; we muſt not thinke that when divers yeeres are run over, the ſame ſcant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling will ſerve. As Common-wealths, ſo Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches have their infancie, youth and man-hood: and ſo ſtill they muſt be clothed and dreſſed up with a more perfect and ſpirituall Diſcipline. The Apoſtle himſelfe alludes to this, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.1. <hi>The heire as long as he is a childe, is under Tutors and Governours.</hi> The Jewiſh Church was a childe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Q. How doth God record ſuch unworthy ſpirits as we ſpeake of with diſgrace?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:111902:11"/>
            <p>
               <hi>R.</hi> By writing, in holy writ, of ſuch men, and their manners, and reckoning them up together, and caſting the words into the eyes, eares and mouthes of men, never to be forgotten, as long as men upon earth have ſenſes. Juſt as the Lord dealt with King <hi>Ahaz,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.22. &amp;c. <hi>And</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>In the time of this diſtreſſe</hi> (that is, that the <hi>Edomites</hi> and <hi>Philiſtims</hi> oppreſſed <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> and the King of <hi>Aſsyria,</hi> being hired to help, helped not, but diſtreſſed him) <hi>did hee,</hi> that is, <hi>Ahaz, treſpaſſe yet more againſt the Lord. This is that King</hi> Ahaz: <hi>For hee ſacrificed to the Gods of</hi> Damaſcus <hi>which ſmote him; and he ſaid, becauſe the Gods of the Kings of</hi> Syria <hi>help them, therefore will I ſacrifice to them, that they may helpe me.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Not for honour, as Demoſthen.</hi> Quam pulchrum eſt digite monſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti dioter hic eſt.</note> See what a pointed-at-man hee is here made for diſgrace. <hi>This is that King</hi> Ahaz, and to the worlds end will it be read of him: So <hi>Jeroboam</hi> by his Idolatry, gat him in ſacred ſtory of <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Chronicles</hi> an addition of title of diſgrace. <hi>Ieroboam the ſonne of</hi> Nebat <hi>that made</hi> Iſrael <hi>to ſinne.</hi> Yea, ſometimes it is of divine providence in a ſpeciall manner, that humane ſtories pen the ill lives of evill men. This is cleare, when as the Holy Ghoſt hath by way of approbation repeated ſuch ſtories; as the <hi>Talmuds</hi> mentioning of <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> their withſtanding <hi>Moſes;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.8.</note> and divers of the <hi>Poets</hi> expreſſions:<note place="margin">1 Tit. 12. p. 28. marg.</note> as that of the <hi>Poet</hi> touching the <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,</hi> of which afore.</p>
            <p n="5">5<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> and laſt Q. <hi>How doth God diſcard and leave them graceleſſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſol.</hi> God leaves them to themſelves, that they ſhall be without the preſence or power of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:111902:12"/>the ordinances that ſhould worke grace in them: as theſe at the generall hurry of <hi>Judah's</hi> returne from <hi>Babylon</hi> (for that could not be <hi>ſine ſtrepitu, ſine alique pulvere,</hi> but ſome notice muſt be taken of it) being not awakened to goe up, fall aſleepe with more then an <hi>Endymion</hi> ſleepe. So there now (as Chriſt ſaid to the drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie Diſciples) they may <hi>ſleepe on;</hi> there they may ſit till their bones ake, yea, till their hearts ake, without a Temple, without a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, without a Prophet,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.</note> without a Prieſt, and without the Congregation of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſo without the pledges of Gods well pleaſed pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence among them. So in all ages, people con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to be without a teaching Miniſter, when time ſerved, and which others tooke, uſually are left long time in that periſhing condition; if ever they live to ſee halfe the like opportunity. But uſually it coſteth many a generation, before that place or people are relieved, eſpecially if a generall opportunity be neglected. Theſe Potters in the Text, are ſtill in <hi>Babylon</hi> in their generations, for ought we know, ſcattered with the ten Tribes, never likely to be relieved till the generall calling of the <hi>Jewes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus of the explication of the Doctrine; next of the <hi>vindication</hi> of it. To cleare it from <hi>Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> and <hi>ſcruples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Object. <hi>God ceaſeth now to write, therefore ceaſeth now to record mens ill manners with diſgrace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> 1. Parallel, or like ſinners and ſinnes will bring them all under the ſame diſgrace. How did <hi>England,</hi> growing cold and formall,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:111902:12"/>like <hi>Laodicea,</hi> cauſe men to call her <hi>Laodicea.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Brigſtman</hi> on <hi>Apocal.</hi> So that <hi>Iohn</hi> in the <hi>Revel.</hi> who ſuffered baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment under the Tyranny of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </note> And <hi>Rome</hi> imitating <hi>Babylon</hi> in perſecution and tyranny to be termed <hi>Babylon;</hi> imitating <hi>Sodome</hi> * in luſt and laſciviouſneſſe, to be termed <hi>Sodome;</hi> and imitating <hi>Egypt</hi> * in Idolatry and ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be termed <hi>Egypt.</hi> 
               <note n="**" place="margin">Revel. <hi>11.8 The Adulteries and Luſt and the Idolatries and Superſtitions of</hi> Rome, <hi>being ſo notorious that Poets have ſung of them.</hi> Mantuan <hi>of her Luſts,</hi> Roma eſt jam totalupanar. <hi>Yea the Heathen Poet</hi> Perſius, Iuvenal <hi>and</hi> Horatius <hi>ſo much and in ſuch groſſe terms as is not meet to be mentioned: So of</hi> Romes <hi>Idolatrie and Superſtition,</hi> Mantuan <hi>thus, Eclog. 9.</hi> Famaeſt Aegyptum coluiſſe animalia qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dam et pronumini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, multas habuiſſe ferarum. Illa ſuperſtitio minor eſt, quam noſtra ferarum. Hic aras habet omue ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, contraria ceyte, Naturares atque Deo, qui dieitur olim, Prapoſuiſſe hominem cunctis animantibus unum. <hi>Yea</hi> Iuvenal <hi>the Heathen Poet of Aegypts ſuperſtition thus. Sat. 15.</hi> Quu neſeit Voluſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Bit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice, qualia demens Aegyptus portenta Colat? Crocodylon adorat pars bac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>la pavet ſaturam ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentibus Ibim. Illic Ceruleos, hic piſcem fluminu, illic, Oppidatota canons venerantur.— Porrum et Cape nefa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> violare et frangere morſu. O ſanctas gentes, quibus ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> naſcuntur in hort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Numin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.—</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It is Gods Divine providence that orders mens pens ſtill, much more then Crowes and Sparrowes; and therefore Gods providence ſo provides, that ſometimes meere men write of the vices of men: as <hi>Livius, Tacitus, &amp;c.</hi> Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times open perſecutors and enemies of all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, write of their owne facts to their owne ſhame: ſo the Records in the offices of BB. and Chancellours and Regiſters in Queene <hi>Maries</hi> dayes preſerved for us a Hiſtory to fill a Booke of Martyrs, of and concerning their owne tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall perſecutions.<note n="(b)" place="margin">Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> neguts quam in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>redibil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſtianorum tun. pudore, tum ettam corum qui vere tales ſun cordolio ut Iuda filia ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tari non liceat. Dei filialiceat. Imo Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>acl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s filia meretricar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> non aliter ante poſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t quam facta per baptiſmur. ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum, Chriſts ſoror, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſpen. de co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>l b. 3. c. 4.</hi>
               </note> The Papiſts themſelves write with deteſtation, that in <hi>Rome</hi> a <hi>Jewiſh</hi> maid might not be admitted into the Stewes of whoredome, unleſſe ſhe would be firſt baptiſed. That 80. Martyrs were put in an houſe by the maſſacrers, and fetcht one by one by the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner to a blood pit, over which hee cut their throats as Calves, hee putting his bloody knife
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:111902:13"/>like a Butcher, in his mouth, whiles hee drag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged another to the pit.<note n="*" place="margin">Book of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Object. <hi>It ſeemes not to ſtand with Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, to caſt them off for graceleſſe; nor with his truth to forſake them, ſeeing he hath ſworne he deſires not the death of a ſinner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> We may ſee in the 65. of <hi>Eſay,</hi> and the firſt ſeven verſes, that when the Lord hath firſt freely and fully revealed himſelfe in his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, then hath he left ſufficient teſtimony of his mercy, and of his willingneſſe that men ſhould not periſh;<note place="margin">2 Chron. 36.16. For them that ſlight the meanes of Grace, there <hi>is no remedy.</hi>
               </note> ſo that if then men come not in by the ordinances, the Lord is diſcharged from all his ingagements, and juſtice is to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in the place of mercie, and to proceed againſt the contemners of mercy.</p>
            <p>Thus alſo of the <hi>vindication:</hi> next of the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation</hi> of this point, by teſtimonie of Scripture. Firſt, wee find in Scripture a propheſie, that this unworthy ſpirit ſhould emaſculate ſome tribes of this <hi>Iewiſh</hi> nation.<note place="margin">Gen. 49.14, 15.</note> That <hi>Iſachar</hi> ſhould <hi>be a ſtrong Aſſe couching downe betweene two burthens;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">It is in the Hebr. without any tenſe of <hi>is,</hi> or <hi>ſhall.</hi> But it is meant in the future tenſe. See v. 1. of that 49. of Gen.</note> 
               <hi>and ſeeing that reſt was good, and that the land was pleaſant, he bowed his ſhoulder to beare, and became a ſervant to tribute;</hi> upon this propheſie of <hi>Iacob</hi> the father of the twelve Tribes, <hi>Moſes</hi> after deſcants, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.18. ſaying, that <hi>Iſachar ſhould rejoyce in his Tents, as</hi> Zabulon <hi>in his going forth,</hi> that is, <hi>Zabulon</hi> ſhould be of an Heroick ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous ſpirit for ſeafairing; and <hi>Iſachar</hi> ſhould be of a duller domeſticke ſpirit, like a Snaile al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes faſtened in the ſhell; or as a Bee, ſucking
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:111902:13"/>the hony in the hive; though both Tribes ſhould partake of worldly bleſſings, the <hi>one by ſea,</hi> the <hi>other by land.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dent. 33.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Nor is this meanneſſe of ſpirit pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied onely of <hi>Iſachar:</hi> but,</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is practiſed alſo by other Tribes; others of them could couch betweene two bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens as well as <hi>Iſachar, Iudges</hi> 5.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. So Iun. <hi>Quand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> quidem ſumit ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones</hi> per Iſiac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem. And to read the words otherwiſe, As to avenge <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> ſeems to overforce the Hebr. phraſe which is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> In ulciſ endo <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ultiones <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which laſt word to reader In Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, were to ſpeak as if the revenge had bin wrought upon Iſrael: Therfore <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> muſt be rendred per, by the means, as ofttimes it is.</note> 
               <hi>Praiſe yee the Lord for taking vengeance</hi> (that is, on the enemies) <hi>by the meanes of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>by the meanes of thoſe of</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael <hi>that offered themſelves willingly:</hi> for it ſeems all came not forth to the battell: Some indeed rode forth voluntarily &amp; valiantly, <hi>v.</hi> 9.10. And <hi>Zebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> &amp; <hi>Napthali</hi> jeoparded their lives to death, <hi>verſ.</hi> 18. But <hi>Deborahs</hi> ſong expoſtulateth wich <hi>Reuben, Gilead, Dan,</hi> and <hi>Aſhur, v.</hi> 16.17. For there was great wondering, that <hi>Reuben,</hi> though divided by <hi>Jordan,</hi> ſhould be divided in heart, at leaſt in hand, at ſuch a time of common danger, wherein they might all have loſt their ſpirituall liberty, for want of a little more helpe; not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gained with much helpe. Therefore the author of this ſong expoſtulates with <hi>Reuben,</hi> why now, after <hi>Iſachar</hi> had left off couching between two burthens, and plaid the men, that <hi>Reuben</hi> would turne <hi>Iſachar,</hi> and couch betweene two bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens? <hi>Why abodeſt thou</hi> (O Reuben) <hi>among the ſheep folds</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">The Heb. word is the ſame, as Gen. 49. is inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted to ſignifie, <hi>Iſachars</hi> Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens. <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> And being in the Dual. Numb. ſign. two Burthens. However we ſound the word; that is the ſenſe, ſome worldly reaſons were as poyſes upon the will, that they would no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> come out to help. They were preſſed down to ſit ſtill, by the love of eaſe and wealth.</note>, <hi>to heare the bleatings of the flockes?</hi> And therefore it is againe repeated, <hi>For the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of</hi> Reuben <hi>there were great ſearchings of heart.</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:111902:14"/>He goes on to the reſt; <hi>And</hi> Gilead <hi>abode beyond</hi> Jordane (that is, the Inhabitants of the Country, or County of <hi>Gilead</hi>) and came not to helpe in the warre, And why did <hi>Dan</hi> remaine in ſhips? <hi>Aſhur</hi> continued on the Sea ſhore, and abode in his breaches, that is, of the Rockes. The ſteepe naturally fenced clifts, forts, or holds in Rocks<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Super fracturas.</note>; yea, adde to all theſe cowards, <hi>Meroz, v.</hi> 23. that is, the <hi>Merozites,</hi> there prophetically curſed with repetition, for not comming out to the help of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, for proofe, let us bring in <hi>Iſrael</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>definitely, without diſtinction of Tribes, that is, a many of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> of all Tribes,<note n="(1)" place="margin">The unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe of their ſpirit.</note> ſhewing abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of baſeneſſe of ſpirit in oppoſition to their deliverance from their former captivity in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> even from the firſt attempt of their liberty, till they came almoſt to enter <hi>Canaan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. When <hi>Moſes</hi> came the firſt time to a few of them, playing the <hi>Praeludium,</hi> making a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to his delivering them under God, killing the <hi>Egyptian</hi> that ſet upon the <hi>Iſraelite;</hi> the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row who ſhould firſt cry out of this,<note place="margin">Exod 2.11.12, 13 14, 15.</note> but a very <hi>Iſraelite?</hi> becauſe <hi>Moſes</hi> did but adviſe him not to wrong his <hi>Iſraelitiſh</hi> brother. This noyſe made <hi>Moſes</hi> flie; and the queſtion about the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> deliverance was laid aſide for forty yeeers, hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in the darke.</p>
            <p n="2">2. At the end of forty yeeres, when the Lord by a fiery buſh, began to bring the matter to light againe, and put <hi>Moſes</hi> on the deſigne of an open, publique regular way of delivering them. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe upon the motion of <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:111902:14"/>let them goe. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> was the worſe, and more harſh to <hi>Iſrael, Iſrael</hi> is angry with <hi>Moſes.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 5.21. comp. cha, 6 v. 9. Yea and at this time ſaid to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Let us alone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that we may ſerve the Egyptians.</hi> Exod. 14.12. See the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bl.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. When they came to the red ſea, there they ſhewed of what ſpirit they were towards their liberty. <hi>And they ſaid unto</hi> Moſes, <hi>becauſe there were no graves in</hi> Egypt, <hi>Haſt thou taken us away to dye in the Wilderneſſe? Wherefore haſt thou dealt thus with us to carry us forth out of</hi> Egypt? <hi>For it had been better for us to ſerve the</hi> Egyptian,<note place="margin">Exod. 14.11, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>then that wee ſhould dye in the Wilderneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. When they come to the Wilderneſſe of Sin, they murmure againſt their deliverance thus farre; <hi>yea, the whole Congregation</hi> (i. e. for the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall) <hi>murmure againſt</hi> Moſes <hi>and</hi> Aaron, <hi>ſaying to them,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exod. 16.1, 2.3.4.</note> 
               <hi>Would to God wee had died by the hand of the Lord in the Land of</hi> Egypt, <hi>when we ſate by the fleſh-pots, and when we did eate bread to the full: For yee have brought us forth into this wilderneſſe to kill this whole aſſembly with hunger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. When their deliverance came as farre as the wilderneſſe of <hi>Riphidim,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exod. 17.1, 2, 3.</note> there they murmure for water: <hi>the people did chide with</hi> Moſes, <hi>and ſaid, Give us water, that we may drinke: And the people thirſted there for water, and the people murmured againſt</hi> Moſes, <hi>and ſaid, wherefore is this, that thou haſt brought us out of</hi> Egypt <hi>to kill us, and our children, and our Cattell with thirſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. And laſtly,<note place="margin">Kades Barnea is a City of the Idu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maeans 40 miles from <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi> Itine ar. I ot. S. Scrip.</note> (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or we will follow them in their humor no further) when they came to <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſh</hi> within 40. miles of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> or therabouts, from whence the ſpies were ſent; when ſome of them returned with tidings of ſome difficulties, though the other ſpake divine demonſtrations
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:111902:15"/>of poſſibility to win the land, the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one of their old fits, but with more violence. <hi>Would we had dyed in</hi> Egypt;<note place="margin">Numb. 14.1, 2, 3.4 5, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 10 11.</note> 
               <hi>were it not better to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to</hi> Egypt? <hi>Come, let us make us a Cap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aine, and returne to</hi> Egypt; <hi>and when</hi> Joſuah <hi>and</hi> Caleb indeavoured with moſt gracious words, and ſtrong conſolations to ſtill them; <hi>ſaying, God was departed from the</hi> Canaanites, <hi>and the Lord is with us; ſo that they ſhall be bread for us:</hi> the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> yea, all the Congregation (<hi>i. e.</hi> for the generall) <hi>bad ſtone them,</hi> i. e. Joſuah <hi>and</hi> Caleb <hi>with ſtones.</hi> Thus by aſcending up a paire of ſtayers of ſixe ſteps you have ſeene the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of theſe men. In whoſe ſtory alſo there is a touch of their ſecret heart preſcribing antiquity:<note place="margin">2. They preſcribe Antiquity.</note> they <hi>ſate</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> that is according to the firſt and proper ſign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in hab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tando nos <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>les we dwelt</hi> by the fleſh pots. 3. The ſordid condition they preferred.</note> by the fleſh pots in <hi>Egypt, Exod.</hi> 16.3. And yet tempted him forty yeeres, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95. In whoſe words and actions there is alſo to be ſeene the <hi>ſordid condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> they preferre, <hi>viz.</hi> an <hi>Egypt</hi> before a <hi>Canaan.</hi> An <hi>Egypt,</hi> that muſt needs be, beſides a moſt toyl-ſome laborious place, a loathſome abominable place to <hi>Iſrael, when</hi> Iſrael <hi>knew what an abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they were to the</hi> Egyptians,<note place="margin">Gen. 46.34 Exod. 8.26.</note> 
               <hi>the</hi> Egyptians <hi>ſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the</hi> Iſraelites <hi>ſacrifices, and their calling of Shepheards, that the</hi> Iſraelites <hi>were put in</hi> Goſhen <hi>by themſelves.</hi> An <hi>Egypt,</hi> that was full of Idolls, they grew in their gardens, crawled on the earth,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>43. marg</note> flew in the ayre, &amp;c. (as we touched afore) and therefore full of Idolatry; and therefore ought to have beene a ſoule abomination to them.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ord</note> And whether God doth not <hi>reproach upon divine record,</hi> this prelation, and eſteem of <hi>Egypt,</hi> let any man judge that obſerves the manner or
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:111902:15"/>ſtile of the ſtory, the phraſe and language of the relation: For the two oppoſite, <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Ioſhua</hi> are commended. <hi>Ergo,</hi> therefore the murmurers diſcommended. Their carriage in this buſineſſe is called <hi>tempting of God;</hi> and becauſe it had been frequent, therefore ſummed up, and numbred to be <hi>ten times;</hi> and becauſe they had iterated their rebellious baſeneſſe of will and words,<note place="margin">Numb 14 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.</note> therefore the Holy Ghoſt repeats the ſumme of all at leaſt three times, in three ſeverall far-diſtant ages. In <hi>Moſes time,</hi> by <hi>Moſes;</hi> in the <hi>time of the Pſalmiſt,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">In Ex. Num. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> afore cited. Pſal. 95. Acts 7.</note> by him; in the <hi>time of Stephan,</hi> by him; and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, obſerve how God caſts them off as <hi>homines per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditos,</hi> loſt men; ſome to periſh in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſome to all impiety in <hi>Egypt,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Kings 23.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 32, 33, 34.</note> and others to be captivated in <hi>Egypt,</hi> or to <hi>Egypt;</hi> or tributary to it: and then you have the full proofe of the whole Doctrine, in every part, made up out of the carriage of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> in relation to <hi>Egypt.</hi> We might adde (but that we have beene ſo long in proofe already) divers things out of the New <hi>Teſtament;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Math. 15.</note> the madneſſe of the <hi>Phariſees</hi> and <hi>Iewes</hi> upon their dirty ceremonies againſt Chriſt,<note place="margin">Mar. 26.61. Acts 7. Acts 21. Acts 19. Acts 14.</note> 
               <hi>Stephan</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> preaching to them Goſpel li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties: The clamours of <hi>Demetrius</hi> and the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> in the behalfe of <hi>Diana,</hi> and her ſilver ſhrines, and of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and <hi>Mercurie,</hi> and divers other paſſages, in Chriſt and the Apoſtles time;<note place="margin">Revel. 17.12, 13, 14. &amp; 18.11, 12. &amp;c to v. 20.</note> and out of the propheſies of the <hi>Revelation:</hi> But it is high time to paſſe to the <hi>demonſtration of this point.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſumme, wee ſhall give but one maine <hi>Reaſon</hi> for demonſtration of this point of Doctr.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:111902:16"/>Therefore doth the Lord ſo deale with refuſers of ſpirituall liberty with ſuch ſeverity, becauſe in refuſing they adde iniquity unto iniquity, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curably. And when God doth impoſe judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by way of gradation, as to <hi>diſgrace,</hi> and <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>card as graceleſſe;</hi> then we may eaſily ſuppoſe that mans ſinnes with aſcending aggravations; when the ſea bank is made high, 'tis becauſe the tide ſwels high: So that man profeſſing, at leaſt practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that unjuſt way o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſinning; God pronounceth this as his juſt way of vengeance in puniſhing. For God is mightily offended with aſcentions and aggravations of ſinne, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.13.</p>
            <p>That we may ſee the aſcent or riſings of this ſinne of the Anti-libertine; of this oppoſite of ſpirituall immunity; note, firſt how it begins in <hi>omiſsion</hi> or <hi>remiſsion,</hi> careleſſneſſe to know the glaſſe and glory of this liberty; ſecondly, that it is radicated, habituated and ſetled in the very <hi>complexion;</hi> or ſetled into a very <hi>complexion;</hi> it becomes his corrupt naturall diſpoſition; third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that it is maintained and continued with a full, if not a profeſt <hi>reſolution;</hi> fourthly, by all is made up an Idolatrous ingratefull retaliation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This ſpirituall vaſſall will not learne nor underſtand what the liberty of the Goſpell is: and thats a ſtrange thing, ſeeing it is <hi>a liberty;</hi> What was our maine occaſion for which the <hi>Jewes</hi> tooke away the life of the Lord Jeſus, but their perverſe blindneſſe,<note place="margin">Math. 27.6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Ioh. 6.</note> ſo much extolled by the morall <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Math. 15.</note> if but civill; they will not indure the light of his glorious Doctrine touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the annulling of <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; the Temple-cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies?
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:111902:16"/>If he did but in ſound of words,<note place="margin">Math. 23.</note> glance at thoſe, they indited the fact as a great crime. What was that which provoked the <hi>Iewes</hi> to the ſtopping their eares, and the martyring of <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts 6.</note> but the Doctrine of the liberty of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, in oppoſition to <hi>Moſaicall</hi> ceremonies?<note place="margin">Acts 7.</note> What kindled the contention betweene the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniouſly imbondaged <hi>Iewes,</hi> and the enfran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſed and freed converts of the <hi>Gentiles:</hi> but the <hi>Jewes</hi> ſticking to the Doctrine of workes and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonious performances?<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o <hi>Rom</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> on all which (that I may t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch the very reaſon of this unteachable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) they were ſo madde,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p to Gala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> not under the notion of bondage, nor did they oppoſe Goſpell liberty under the conceipt of liberty: but man natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loves a ſenſible ſervice, and loathes a ſpirituall worſhip, that hee may ſeeme to himſelfe to be able of himſelfe to doe ſomewhat for himſelfe in matters of ſalvation. This makes the <hi>Papiſts</hi> to turne all their worſhip into (as the Apoſtle calls it) a <hi>bodily exerciſe;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.8.</note> as formerly the <hi>Coloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> into <hi>luſt not, touch not, handle not;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Coloſſ. 2.</note> and <hi>an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting of the body.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">See the accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs in the Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an perſecutions: <hi>Fox</hi> Book of Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> The <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſacrament of the Supper, is the fleſh &amp; blood, and bones of Chriſt. The water of Baptiſme waſheth away originall ſin: Their repentance, whippings and Lent, and fleſh faſts and almoſt all their ſervices are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their doctrine, efficacious <hi>ex opere ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rato;</hi> their bare doing the duty, doth effectually do the ſpirituall thing. So the Popiſh Prelaticall faction turne all worſhip and devotion into ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ceremonious actions and motions. Now this firſt ſtep is an high one, even ignorance,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:111902:17"/>eſpecially affected ignorance;<note place="margin">2 Theſſ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.8.</note> for it is that which ſtops up the way againſt the light, and makes men to wander in every way of ſinne.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Such perſons as theſe that will not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the excellency of their liberty, but ſtand out againſt it with cuſtome, naturallize them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into a liberty-loathing or depiſing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion. So that as the great Philoſopher ſaid,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <q>ſome are ſervants by nature. Fooliſh, paſſive, ſilly, in regard of governing others, but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of ſubjection to be governed, they are <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumenta rationalia,</hi> they have reaſon enough to work according to the direction of another.</q> So theſe men by corrupt cuſtome, are fitted to be led by the ſtreame of times, and the examples of corrupt men, and the rotten principles of blind guides. There is that power, or rather tyranny of a vaine converſation received by <hi>tradition,</hi> that nothing but a redemption, and that by the blood of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> will fetch a man off, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18. Wee ſee to this day, the ſad event of this truth. How hard it is to take off the old wives, and doting men, and idiots of all ſorts from their old <hi>mump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimus.</hi> That as conſcientious perſons wander for the pure practiſing of the word, the meat of their ſoules; ſo theſe traditious perſons wander for their pottage. And alas for them, what meane they make for Swines broth! Sure, if this ſtuffe were of God, the rude multitude would never be ſo eager; they would not cry out that reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were <hi>Innovation.</hi> But ſure their broth is not good, their meat is ſo bad, <hi>Eſay</hi> 65.4. <hi>They eate Swines fleſh, and broth of abominable things is in their
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:111902:17"/>veſſells.</hi> Certainely the beſt prayers, the beſt formes of worſhip are not commonly conſiſtent with the worſt kind of life: But as theſe pottage-bellies, theſe Swine-eaters, of which the Prophet ſpeaks, <hi>live among graves and monuments;</hi> ſo theſe that cry up cuſtomary forms of Diſcipline, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, though corrupted, live commonly among the dead, they love the company at the beſt but of the Phariſaicall <hi>painted Sepulchors.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> But to breake off to goe to the next head, wee ſee, wee heare, wee know, that cuſtome hath, and doth prove another nature, a new co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plexion to men, to hold them ſtrong to their cuſtomary way of worſhip and Diſcipline, be it never ſo much cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted and degenerated.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To all this the oppoſers or contemners of liberty, add reſolution: they know no better, as we ſaid in the firſt Branch; they are accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to this condition, as we ſaid in the ſecond. Therefore they reſolve, and ſometimes profeſſe their reſolution, that they will not goe out free, they will not, becauſe they will not. As the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill ſervant, <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.6. So theſe ſpirituall vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals in effect ſay, <hi>They love their Maſter, they will not goe out free.</hi> For, obſerve their reliſh of, and carriage towards the ſound preaching of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall liberty, of, and toward the word that muſt ſet them free, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.32, 33, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And you ſhall finde that they deſpiſe it. And to deſpiſe the word, is to make ones ſelfe incurably culpable, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.15, 16. The leaſt that can befall them in this life, is, that <hi>they ſhall have their eares bored, and ſhall ſerve their old Maſter for ever.</hi> As to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:111902:18"/>the eare ſignifies knowledge;<note place="margin">Ruth. Pſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> ſo to <hi>boare</hi> the eare, ſignifies obedience: ſo theſe not learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the truth, ſhall be obliged in obedience to all doctrines of ſpirituall vaſſallage; they ſhall, (as the Apoſtle ſpeakes)<note place="margin">2 Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 11.20.</note> 
               <hi>ſuffer</hi> i.e. <hi>contentedly, if a man bring them into bondage, if a man devoure them, if a man take of them.</hi> Have we not ſeene this? Have we not ſeene men of the ceremonious way, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to any coſt impoſed by their ſuperſtitious taske-maſters, for a ſtate-diſturbing project, when as they are ready to roare out complaints againſt a religious and regular way, requiring halfe the charge towards reformation.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Out of all theſe, the <hi>Antagoniſts</hi> of liberty hatch up an ingratefull Idolatrous retaliation. Theſe men will not come out of the ditch, they thanke you; they Idolatrouſly love their bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage better then God or his liberty; all their requitall to God is, hee may take his labour for his travell, and his expectation in vaine for his charges <hi>to ſend to theſe men,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>and riſing up betimes, and ſending,</hi> to bring them out of their ſlavery. Of ſuch ingratitude, the Lord complaines bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.6. <hi>Do yee thus requite the Lord, O fooliſh people, and unwiſe? Is not he thy father that bought thee?</hi> Though God hath <hi>bought</hi> them liberty with the precious blood of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> yet theſe vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals will not go out free. God bitterly threatens unthankfulneſſe;<note place="margin">Prov. 17.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> a plaine ſigne that theſe are of the unthankfulleſt ſort of men,<note place="margin">2 T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> becauſe of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanctifiedſt ſort of men. The greateſt neglecters of ſpirituall liberty, are the greateſt loathers of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And what ſin more unreaſonable in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:111902:18"/>perſon, then unthankfulneſſe? And what more provoke full of the perſon offended, than unthankfulneſſe? This is a naturall prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple in all men, to let fall ſquab in the dirt one that ſtrikes him, that almoſt puld him out.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee the liberty loathing man, illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate in the firſt degree, illiberall even ſo in nature and diſpoſition in the ſecond;<note place="margin">* By all ſoure man 1. would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace liberty, therfore God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords him with diſgrace.</note> irrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally reſolute in the third; reſolutely perem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptorily Idolatrouſly ingratefull in the fourth; opportunely therefore God comes in with his Divine vengeance-maxims:<note place="margin">2 He would caſt off God the fore God diſcards him.</note> 
               <hi>What meaſure ye meat ſhall be meated to you againe; with the froward God will ſhew himſelfe froward.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Math. 7.2.</note> If man will riſe by ſteps in ſinne, God will riſe by ſteps in his judgements.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 18.26.</note> Three times God raiſeth his note of threatning, <hi>Levit.</hi> 26. againſt the deſpiſer of his Word of Wiſedome and Counſell: and hee raiſeth it by ſevens, and thoſe are diſcords in Muſique. Such ſayings will be heavie ſongs, and their executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on heavie Pangs to the wicked. In the 21. <hi>verſe</hi> hee ſaith, <hi>If yee walke contrary to me, and will not hearken to me, I will bring ſeven times more plagues upon you according to your ſinnes.</hi> And in <hi>verſe</hi> 23.24. hee addes, <hi>If you will not be reformed by theſe things, I will puniſh you yet ſeven times more:</hi> And yet further addes, <hi>verſe</hi> 27. And if you will not for <hi>all</hi> this obſerve the <hi>(All) Hearken unto mee, then will I walke contrary to you in fury,</hi> (marke the addition) <hi>I, even I,</hi> note alſo that reduplication, <hi>will chaſtice you ſeven times for your ſinnes.</hi> It is not ſaid ſeven times more, as intimating a period, but indefinitely, they ſhall not know the end
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:111902:19"/>of his judgements. I can hardly hold my peace from intimating how God plagued this Land, perhaps about ſeven yeeres, in the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, by irregular Counſels, then ſeven yeeres more in the Church, in the time of our new bbb. the <hi>Arochronogram</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> I warrant you will thinke I meane not <hi>William</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror, but <hi>William</hi> the Corrupter. But thinke as you pleaſe, I will ſay no more of that by ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition and perſecution. And ſince that in Church and Commonwealth, both, as if the laſt ſeven yeeres were now concurrent. And why? I doubt, becauſe we are not weary of ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or at leaſt, doe not deſire reformation. When <hi>the Iſraelite,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exod. 2.</note> 
               <hi>I</hi> ſay <hi>the Iſraelite,</hi> for it was but <hi>one</hi> of them, clamoured againſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> beginning to deliver them, it coſt all <hi>Iſrael</hi> forty yeeres bondage longer for it, as we heard afore. How much more may one thouſand, yea, one million of ſuch perverſe ſpirits hinder the <hi>Churches</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance many faire yeer? I am ſure <hi>Iſrael</hi> got out of <hi>Egypt</hi> when they willingly &amp; haſtily packed up to depart from <hi>Egypt,</hi> not when they murmured againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> When the hearts of a Nation depart from the abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of a nation, then ſhall the abominations be made to depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a nation. But whiles the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of a people will not conceive what is ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall liberty, nor receive it, but reſolve againſt it, God wil fil ſuch people with the filth and foyl of their own ways. I have been long in the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, yet not without reaſon. Therefore thinke it not tedious if I give ſome particular inſtance, and then I will ſtep to application.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:111902:19"/>
            <p n="1">1. Will men imbrace Idols (and an Idol is any <hi>medium cultus,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">This I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon 2 Pet. 3.</note> any meane of worſhip which is not of Divine inſtitution) though God hath revealed himſelfe to the contrary? God hath recorded this for their diſgrace, that thus they ſhall be diſcarded as graceleſſe,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 4.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Ephraim is joyned unto Idols, let him alone.</hi> As if the Lord ſhould ſay, eare and burſt; or commit ſpirituall whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome till thou haſt got the filthy diſeaſe of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable ſottiſh ſinning to damnation: ſo <hi>Rome</hi> for that is left, no more <hi>Hus</hi> or <hi>Luther</hi> ſent; no more ſuch a Gooſe or Swan ſent to waken their Capitol, let in their <hi>Tr. Councel</hi> to curſe the truth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Will men <hi>have many altars to ſinne?</hi> God hath recorded this for their diſgrace, that thus they ſhall be diſcarded as graceleſſe, <hi>that altars ſhall be unto them to ſinne,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 8.11.</note> becauſe <hi>Ephraim hath made many altars to ſinne, altar ſhall be unto him to ſinne;</hi> as if the Lord ſhould ſay, <hi>Ephraim</hi> hath made there, and thoſe altars; and thus many, more then ever I appointed or approved, and ſo ſinnes in making of them; (though altars were then in uſe) therefore they ſhall ſinne abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in ſacrificing upon them, or worſhipping at them; and their lawleſſe worſhip ſhall produce in them a leud life; their multiplied Idolatry, ſhall multiply impiety: obſerve thoſe men that by change of times became ſo <hi>altared.</hi> How in their lives became altered? How ſoone did that bow-backed faction fall as it were downe, and tumble in the dirt of prophaneneſſe?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Will men ſerve God after their owne fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhions and phantaſies, as to preſume to make any
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:111902:20"/>thing (though one of his owne creatures) a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of God preſent with them, through which to worſhip God, which <hi>God</hi> never com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded? This in Gods opinion, is to turne him into the Image of that repreſentation of that creature whatſoever it be,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om 1, 21, 22, 23, 24.</note> and for that God will give them up. Read the place conſiderably, and you ſhall finde, that to make a croſſe a repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Chriſt, through which to looke upon Chriſt, is to turne Chriſt into a croſſe; to take the bread in the ſacrament, and through or to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it to worſhip Chriſt as a <hi>medium adoratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis</hi> a meane of adoration,<note place="margin">Apt.</note> and not onely of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation, is <hi>bread-worſhip,</hi> ſuch men wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the bread, not Chriſt. So that the Popiſh diſtinction of <hi>objectum relativum, ſeu repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivum, &amp; terminativum, in point of ſenſible worſhip deviſed by man, comes to coincidere,</hi> I meane, that all things deviſed by man to looke on, as repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations of God, or Chriſt, whereby to carry them on to worſhip God himſelfe, and Chriſt himſelfe, doe abſolutely in Gods account ſtay their devotion and worſhip there at the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; it doth not radiat through; it is not ſtrained through the groſſe Idol, even to come neere Gods acceptance as unto him. The King of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven concludes, that whiles ſhe that ſaith, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. 7. Shee is a Queene, ſtands kiſſing and comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting with his ſervants, the dumbe creatures, that ſhee is not his ſpirituall loyall Queene, but an Harlot, yea, the mother of Harlots, making all thoſe to be ſpirituall Harlots whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hee teacheth ſo to doe, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.5.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:111902:20"/>
            <p n="4">4. Will men put all holineſſe in outward ſhewes, to ſeeme to men to be devout, in bodily performances to have praiſe from men; as in cringes, creepings, noddings, moppings, or any other antick motions? The Lord returnes them this anſwer, <hi>Ite,</hi> be packing, you have that for your reward, That, and that in this life, and no more, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.5.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Will men put Religion in a ceremony, though once Divinely inſtituted? much more with men will place Religion in humane inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ceremonies; ſo that their Cake is dough, if things be not ceremoniouſly done? The earth muſt be diſquieted, if with thoſe rattles they be not quieted? Chriſt ſhall be queſtioned, if hee eate with unwaſhen hands; then will the Lord ſay to a people, Take, eate, ſurfeit with thy cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, but they ſhall not profit thee, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.13. The obſervation of traditions doth evacuate and anull true adoration. And the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.2. <hi>If yee be circumciſed, Chriſt ſhall profit you nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Would men advance a <hi>reſtrained way of prayer,</hi> I ſay, <hi>a reſtrained</hi> more or leſſe, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance it? be proud of a crutch, and uſe it when the leg is well, would they chiefely have ſuch a way, as generally <hi>periſheth with the uſing?</hi> As Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts reſt in ſuch words; ſo many ſhort <hi>Avema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rics,</hi> &amp;c. till all the Beads be knocked downe? Would not people willingly have their <hi>Miniſters</hi> to uſe <hi>ſuch gifts as Chriſt gives to men, ſince his aſcending up on high and led captivity captive?</hi> Men ſhall have ſuch wayes formes, Miniſters, and long
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:111902:21"/>enough, <hi>comp. Engl.</hi> with <hi>Fr. Den Scot.</hi> Church. But theſe things God records as faults, <hi>Job</hi> 15.4. If to reſtraine in whole be a great fault, then to reſtraine it in part is a fault, though a leſſe one, <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 2.22. No true devotion <hi>reſts</hi> in cut ſcantlings of the ſame ſize and faſhion for all times and occaſions, eſpecially when they leave no more impreſſions of devotion on men gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, then the words and noyſe at the very times of uſing, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11. Miniſters have gifts from Chriſt, not from men; And ſuch as are for the <hi>perfecting,</hi> not the ſtinting or ſtunting of the Saints, when the Church was new borne out of the bloody perſecution of Popery, ſhe might be ſwadled up in clouts and ſwathbands of a ſmall ſcantling, but now ſhe is a woman, ſhe ſhold have large looſe garments, as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> wore, when at men and womans eſtate; ſure the Church ſhould have leave according to the leave of Gods boſome and lap, to ſtretch her limbs, and grow.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Doe men love blinde guides, bad guides, ſoule-ſtarvers, Religion-ſtroyers? they ſhall have them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.14. <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.31. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.9.</p>
            <p n="8">8. To cloſe up the Reaſon: If any ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe any liberty that God offers them, they ſhall have their bellifulls to ſervitude. Theſe <hi>Potters</hi> had enough of it in <hi>Babylon,</hi> both ſpirituall and corporall; and as the ſervant that would not goe free, was bored to ſerve for ever: So thoſe that will not accept of Chriſt and his liberties, who had his eare bored, <hi>Pſal</hi> 40. that wee might goe free, ſhall dye in their ſinnes, and periſh as ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall bondſlaves, <hi>Joh</hi> 8. <hi>ver.</hi> 36. compared with <hi>verſe</hi> 44.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:111902:21"/>
            <p>So that the <hi>Cardo</hi> or main hinge of the reaſon moves upon this; <hi>Gods</hi> moſt wiſe and juſt reta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation: as an eye for an eye, ſo blindneſſe for blindneſſe, a leaving in bondage, for a loving of bondage; <hi>Ma.</hi> 13.14. —<hi>Nec lex eſt juſtior ulla,</hi>
               <q>Quàm necis artifices arte perire ſuâ.</q>
No juſter Law then that men of wicked devices ſhould periſh by their owne devices, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10 2. <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.31. and this is moſt apparantly fulfilled upon liberty loathers, where hath beene the longeſt and largeſt revelation of <hi>God</hi> in his Word, whether to a Towne more then a perſon; or to a County more then a Towne; or to a Kingdome more then a County.</p>
            <p>Uſeful is this Doct. for
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Examination,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Reprehenſion,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Exhortation,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Examination,</hi> to finde the Character of a Cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e; the complexion of a carnall man; a man of whom, if you ſay there is no hurt in him; I will ſay there is no good in him, yea, Chriſt will ſay, there is ſome danger in him, you had need (ſaith Chriſt) beware of <hi>men, Matth.</hi> 10.17. A meere man, a dangerous man. And who more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to hinder reformation, then men morally good; good in civill actions, but ſpiritually bad, bad in ſpirit. The man I am to ſpeake of is ſuch a one, of whom, if you ſay it doth not appeare that the ſpirit of the Divell is in him; yet I affirme out of <hi>Gods</hi> Word, that the ſpirit of <hi>God</hi> is not in him; <hi>Senſuall, not having the ſpirit, Jud.</hi> 5. 10. yea, they have <hi>the ſpirit of the World,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 12. and this is that by which I muſt find him out,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:111902:22"/>even by his worldly, or world-like ſpirit. The Text &amp; doctrine caſt me upon that; for he is not painted out by outward groſſe impieties, but is charactariſed by his baſe minde, and Peaſant-like ſpirit. In generall, he is of an illiberall or illibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſpirit of a noningenuous ſpirit towards ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals: he is an Antilibertine ſpiritually; he is an Antagoniſt, and oppoſite to ſpirituall liberty.</p>
            <p>In particular; he is in relation to acceptance of ſpirituall liberty of A
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Meane,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Negligent,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Secure.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Perverted,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
Spirit.</p>
            <p>Theſe appeare in the Text and Doctrine; on theſe therefore we ſhall inſiſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Of a <hi>meane</hi> or low ſpirit, <hi>Theſe Potters, &amp;c.</hi> flew as low as the dirt: the worke was dirt, and the Workman was dirt; in the worſt ſenſe, <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriam ſuper abat opus,</hi> they wrought in morter, with an unmortified mind; They tempered the dirt with and earthly mind; they were not like the labourers that were <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> workemen, to build the wall of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> holding the Spade or Trewall in his hand, and having his Sword by his ſide, and his eare attentive to the ſound of the Trumpet, to reſiſt the enemies of the <hi>Church,</hi> in caſe they had ſet upon them: not like that late Martyr, who, though one of the greateſt Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and Chriſtians in Chriſtendome, yet in ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, or flight for conſcience, ſerved the <hi>Mayſon.</hi> Be bold, his minde was above his hodd; but to theſe men their mind, and that an earthly one, a dirty one is to them a Kingdome, yea, more then a kingdome, more than the Kingdome of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:111902:22"/>
               <hi>Judea,</hi> the Kingdome where the only Church in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited And thus it is with all ſuch carnall mean low-ſpirited men, matters of Religion, Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Salvation, are but <hi>Queſtions</hi> of <hi>quiddities,</hi> unworthy the conſideration: outward pomp, and carnall peace &amp; plenty, thoſe are material things:<note place="margin">Acts 23.29.</note> matters of Religion to the moſt learned worldly minded man, are but <hi>newalties</hi> and <hi>ſtrange</hi> things:<note place="margin">Acts 17.19.20.</note> they lye without their <hi>Sphere</hi> and <hi>Compaſſe;</hi> the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the <hi>Church,</hi> the reſtauration of the <hi>Church</hi> is nothing to them, ſo they paſſe it by, <hi>Lam</hi> 1.12. Their ſpirits are not <hi>large</hi> enough for ſuch conſiderations: It is as bad as conjuring, to tell them they muſt ſtand within the circle of the reformation of the <hi>Church,</hi> and be a member of the <hi>Church,</hi> if they will be ſaved. As theſe Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, &amp;c. So all of the carnall, whom,
<q>Non meliore luto finxit praecordia Titan,</q>
we find to be of the ſame dirt, thinke that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the <hi>Church</hi> is ſalvation to be had; they thinke not that their welfare conſiſts in <hi>puncto,</hi> in the middle of the <hi>Church,</hi> though Chriſt be there; they are not of <hi>Davids</hi> minde, that prayed for the proſperity of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> that hee might proſper;<note place="margin">pſalme 122.</note> they conſider not the afflictions of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> though the not conſideration brings them into captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with the firſt; ſo that indeed theſe men are not of a faithful,<note place="margin">Amos 6.</note> 
               <hi>loyall</hi> and loving ſpirit towards themſelves; ſuch a man as this findes not what can be higher then himſelfe; hee conceives not how he may be raiſd above himſelf by a gracious ſpirit; he is in effect a <hi>Pelagian</hi> or <hi>Arminian,</hi> good parts of nature are with him grace, 1 <hi>King</hi> 22.24. he is in effect a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> he hold <hi>op <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>opera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> a work
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:111902:23"/>that is ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rially good, is with him a good work <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>8.3 yea, he is worſe yet; he is an Ido<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rous worldling; a worke is with him a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ood worke, a civill worke; a gainfull worke is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, a godly worke with him; <hi>gaine is god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ,</hi> 1 <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m.</hi> 6. Theſe <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>otters, &amp;c.</hi> ſure enough did not ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d themſelves guilty of ungodlineſſe, whiles they preferred this morter before the goodly ſtones of the temple, whiles they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erred theſe pots before the curious Lavers, mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, and golden Baſons of Gods Houſe; their hearts in the faſtening to their bowels is broa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt; the broadeſt part is next themſelves; they are all for themſelves. To ſet forth this meane low-ſpirited man more diſtinctly; his meane ſpirit is an <hi>imbaſed ſpirit,</hi> it is degenerated, from governours in <hi>Moab,</hi> and workers in linnen, they fall to be day-labourers, or clay-labourers; of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> or <hi>Iewes,</hi> they become <hi>Babylonians:</hi> and ſo all men of this ſtraine that live in the <hi>Church,</hi> they are baptiſed, called, &amp;c. as being for Chriſt; they plot, they plead, as if they were Antichriſt, at leaſt they plot,<note place="margin">Revel. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om chap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> they plead for Antichriſt; for the tayle, if not for the head; and the tayle of the Dragon did much hurt, ſwept downe the Starres: Popiſh ceremonies have ſwept downe the Starres, the good Angels of the Church, when erronious doctrines never indangered the peace of the bad. How many of late dayes have degenerated from their Anceſtors; their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers blood ſometimes boyled in their hearts with z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>le and prayer, ſometimes ſparckled in their faces in bold confeſſion of the truth; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times flowed into the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in martyrdome for the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:111902:23"/>truth; and theſe men gladly owne their names and kinne, in the bookes of Martyrs; but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline the imitation of them. When did theſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſed degenerated ſpirits dye their faces with a bluſh to heare profeſſion diſgraced? When heat they their blood in the heart with prayer? When dipped they their foot in ſweat to goe in the behalfe of the Church? yea, when did they ever wet an hayre of their horſes, to ride for a Chriſtian or a good cauſe?</p>
            <p>Againe, this meane ſpirit is a <hi>Cowed ſpirit,</hi> a cowardly ſpirit. <hi>Theſe Potters, &amp;c.</hi> once conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, are for ever conquered, they cannot raiſe their ſpirits above an habituated vaſſalage; the meane ſpirited man thus cowed, can eaſily fall with the times, but not riſe with the times. If lately times have been hard; profeſſion out of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion; he was no egregious man that could not make voyd the Law, and evacuate the Goſpell; caſt off profeſſion, and give large diſpenſations to conſcience. Since that, this meane cowed ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited man i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtinted, or ſtunted (as you ſpeake) in goodneſſe, his legs are aſleep, and his toung ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with the palſie: hee is aſhamed to returne to profeſſion, leſt he ſhould ſeeme to be contrary to himſelf, left times ſhould turn againe to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to him: he cannot tell how for ſhame, to fall in with God, or fall out with ſpirituall bondage.</p>
            <p>Againe, this meane ſpirit is a <hi>puſilanimous ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> a petty ſpirit, looking a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſmall things; as theſe <hi>Potters,</hi> reſt in the name of <hi>Iewes,</hi> but care not for the priviledges, parts and properties of <hi>Iewes:</hi> So this meane petty ſpirit, where ever it
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:111902:24"/>be, lookes more at ſmall things then at great things; he lookes at earthly things in generall above ſpirituall;<note place="margin">Matthew 22.</note> a Farme, an Oxe, a wedding, luſt is more to him than to come to the marriage feaſt of Chriſt: Hee preferres an exchange be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a change; and like the <hi>Emperour</hi> that ſaved the urine of his Subjects, hee prizeth the filth of the world. And if he muſt looke upon <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> hee lookes upon as little of it, as little things of it as may be; upon <hi>Mint,</hi> upon minute things; upon <hi>Cummin,</hi> upon bare comming to the ordinary: His poſition of <hi>Religion</hi> is that of machiavel of Morall vertue, the ſhew of it is uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, the practice cumberſome.</p>
            <p>Againe, this meane low ſpirit is a <hi>private ſpirit;</hi> the meane ſpirited man, is a man of a private ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; <hi>totus inſe,</hi> like the <hi>Snayle,</hi> ſtill within doores at home:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.</note> he is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a meere Animall. And no wonder then that he neglects all but that which tends to his owne welfare; and though hee may goe to the ordinances of <hi>God,</hi> yet hee ſeeks himſelf,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 9.14.</note> as the <hi>Snail</hi> creeping abroad out of the walls or hedges, yet ſtil keeps within it's own houſe. And though he may ſeeme to buſſle in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon good ſometimes, in ſome things; yet it is out of private ends, and higher then that levell, his deſires and bent of ſpirit will not runne. If the wheeles be not oyled with his owne ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, they goe heavily; howbeit, whiles hee thus ſeekes himſelfe, hee loſeth himſelfe: As the Sailers in a ſtorme ſhipwrack themſelves, if every one cares onely for his owne cabinet: a ſtone in an Arch muſt needs fall if left alone,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:111902:24"/>whiles this man fixeth the ſharp ends of his heart downward towards the earth, towards the round world, he cannot be eſtabliſhed. Chriſt is among the Mirtle trees, <hi>Zach.</hi> 1. Among the Tribes in the type of the Ark, <hi>Num.</hi> 2. Among the Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks, <hi>Revel.</hi> 1. The private ſpirit therefore neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting the <hi>Church,</hi> neglects Chriſt, the eldeſt brother, in whom every ſonne of God muſt have his legacie.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, this meane ſpirited man is of a <hi>ſtraiten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſpirit;</hi> This man cannot advance his indeavour, hee cannot mend his pace on any good occaſion. Where theſe <hi>Potters</hi> were, there they are. This opportunity of their returne, ſtirres not them. The ſtrait ſpirited men are like the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſtill in the dark: like the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in themſelves; they can goe but their pack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horſe pace, in frozen formes, generall prayers, eye-profeſſion, &amp;c. If their wives or children were ſicke, or in danger, they would doe leſſe for themſelves, and more for them. But the more the <hi>Church</hi> is ſicke, the more they looke after their owne occaſions.</p>
            <p>I indeavour to ſet forth the firſt branch of this liberty-loathers ſpirit, that he is a man of a mean ſpirit, but I cannot ſatisfie my ſelfe, no wonder therefore if I ſatisfie not others. Theſe <hi>Potters</hi> are not reported for any haynous prancks; mean ſpirited men may be are free from foule facts. But note the place where you finde them, and the times when; ſo that a man may ſay to them ordinarily, as the Lord did once upon a ſpeciall occaſion to <hi>Elijah, What doe you here?</hi> If you were
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:111902:25"/>men of a right ſpirit, what doe you puſling in the world, when you ſhould be for the <hi>Church?</hi> what doe you in your owne houſes, when you ſhould be at the <hi>Parliament?</hi> What doe you contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for earthly things, when you ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting for heavenly? What doe you in carnall private ſpirited mens company, when you ſhould be pleading to the Worthies of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> In ſumme, this meane ſpirited man hath not in him a <hi>mans</hi> ſpirit.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>On the contrary, the godly man that hath learned and lowed his liberty in Chriſt, his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty in the Goſpel, to his power and place, is of an eminent heretiques ſpirit, he could wiſh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe an <hi>Argos,</hi> a man of an hundred eyes, to watch the <hi>Churches</hi> welfare, and warne her of danger. He could wiſh himſefe as <hi>Briaries,</hi> of an hundred hands to doe for the publique cauſe; and of fifty bellies or bowels to compaſſionate her more. Hee makes good his Scutchion to be of the <hi>Lyon,</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>Judah. Abraham</hi> willing to plant a <hi>Church,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b 11.</note> forgat his owne things, and followed God into a ſtrange Countrey. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> mindes amidſt all his owne miſeries, the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of <hi>Hieruſalem, Pſal.</hi> 51. And the more Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſticall and impious the enemies of the <hi>Church</hi> are, the leſſe are the thoughts of the <hi>Church</hi> put out of the hearts of the Saints; the more the Saints mind &amp; deſire the welfare of the <hi>Church, Pſal.</hi> 14. <hi>verſ</hi> laſt, compared with <hi>verſ.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Thus you have ſeene the firſt note of this illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate ſpirited man, of how <hi>mean</hi> a ſpirited man he is. The dimenſions, proportions or meaſures
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:111902:25"/>of his ſpirit, prove very ſmall, very ſcanty. The height, depth, length, breadth of his ſpirit are very minims, petty, and as nothing: For <hi>depth,</hi> his ſpirit is as profound as deepe as the clay pits and uncleane dirt in <hi>Babylon;</hi> as the Bricke-kilnes, as <hi>Leekes</hi> and <hi>Onions</hi> in <hi>Egypt;</hi> as humane inventions, and ſoule-bondages of the place where he lives; as <hi>high</hi> as the <hi>Potters</hi> wheele, as the heaps of burnt Bricks, as high as hee can ſtand up-right. Hee climbes not with <hi>Zacheus</hi> to ſee a Chriſt, to heare the voyce of Chriſt, ſalvation, ſoule-deliverance is come to thine houſe: as <hi>long</hi> as his armes; what hee can reach to by his ſenſes and ſenſible actions. He is naturall, ſavours not the things of the ſpirit. The <hi>breadth,</hi> as broad as <hi>Babylon,</hi> as <hi>Egypt:</hi> He will be in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and of <hi>Babylon,</hi> in <hi>Egypt</hi> and of <hi>Egypt,</hi> rather then to trouble himſelfe to come out of them, with feet or affections, that hee may touch no uncleane thing. His ſpirit is as <hi>low</hi> as a cowards: as <hi>high</hi> as a ſelfe-ſeekers: as <hi>long</hi> as the baſeſt of his anceſtors: As <hi>broad</hi> as his owne par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular way. And to all, adde his activity; he is not like other ſmaller creature, to recompence the ſmalneſſe of bulke, with greatneſſe of activi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; as ſmaller birds, men, &amp;c. But is like filthy naſty vermin, to be ſmall, and to crowle: He is like a <hi>Snayl,</hi> as wel in motion, as keeping at home with his owne advantages. This man will be, and doe in Religion as little as he can for ſhame.</p>
            <p>Whereas the free ſpirited man reaching as high as heaven, as low as the deepeſt corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his heart, as long as eternity, as wide as
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:111902:26"/>the univerſall <hi>Church,</hi> is as active as lightning; he will prayer-blaſt the enemies of the <hi>Church. Amalek</hi> is beaten downe by that hee could not ſee: By <hi>Moſes</hi> praying, rather then by <hi>Joſhuah</hi> fighting; for when <hi>Moſes</hi> ſlacked, <hi>Joſhuah</hi> gave ground. Yea, he is ſo active, that hee is like the Sunne beames, whiles they are on earth, they are in heaven too. <hi>Nehemiah</hi> talkes to the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and to the eternall King of Heaven, and all at a time, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 2.4.5.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This liberty-loather is of a negligent ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, apt to loſe the moſt golden opportunities through leaden negligence. Nor the name of <hi>Jewes,</hi> nor the noyſe of the Kings Proclamation, nor the ſtirres among the <hi>Iewes</hi> to packe away, nor the fame of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> nor the ſenſe of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage could move theſe <hi>Potters</hi> of a negligent ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to take opportunitie of returning to their bodily and ſpirituall liberty. They cannot put an <hi>Emphaſis</hi> at <hi>this</hi> or that ſpeciall time, as <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decai</hi> did to <hi>Heſter.</hi> Who knowes whether thou waſt not advanced for ſuch a time as <hi>this?</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou ſhalt do well to hold thy peace at <hi>this</hi> time. Such kind of men as theſe wee ſpeake of, are of an unprepared ſpirit, and therefore of an opportunity-loſing ſpirit. See a remarkeable place, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.14. So <hi>Saul</hi> loſt his eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in his Kingdome by loſſe of waiting for, and watching one opportunity.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 13.</note> And thouſands loſe their comfort, and find their remedileſſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, by not obſerving every one his owne op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portune time God offers unto his hands.<note place="margin">Eccle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 9.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Iewes</hi> loſe much time of comfort, by ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:111902:26"/>the time to build the houſe of the Lord was not yet come, whiles they deferred,<note place="margin">Hag. 1 1. comp. chap. 2.15 18.</note> they had fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine &amp; want, whiles they built and went on they proſpered. What a loſſe had they in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that in forty yeeres could not know their time?<note place="margin">Pſal. 85.</note> and how irrecoverably undone was <hi>Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> for not knowing her day, <hi>even that her day?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luk. 19.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> The fooliſh Virgins alſo, by loſſe of opportunity, loſt Chriſt and heaven, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. I need not multiply places; the caſe is too cleare, that ſuch ſpirited men will eaſily loſe the opportunity of obtaining of that ſpirituall thing what ever it be that is offered them, and conſequently of that ſpirituall liberty; for they care not. Some let ſlip thoſe occaſions which God hath appointed to be in the preſent Tenſe, and theſe men are conſtantly in the Future. The Lord cries, <hi>to day</hi> if you will heare, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. And <hi>now it is the accepted time, now is the day of ſalvation,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2. But this negligent ſpirit (as once <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) cries, <hi>cras Domine,</hi> to morrow Lord; his repentance is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journed to the day of his death. And all his good deeds exiſt and have their being onely in the purpoſe: his will and his teſtament are alike, they both take force at laſt; at laſt hee hath a <hi>will</hi> to doe good, if hee had time. And at laſt, hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath'd his good deeds by <hi>teſtament,</hi> becauſe he cennot live to doe evill any longer, yea, although God offers him ſome more ſpeciall preſent time opportunities, apples of gold, with pictures of ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Diamonds pointed with gold, ſtriped with <hi>Ophir,</hi> yet he cannot be enamoured with them. Some ſuch God offers him for himſelfe. Heart knocking time, <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.20. If a man did but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:111902:27"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:111902:27"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:111902:28"/>theſe, he may be made for ever, ſo <hi>Pſa.</hi> 27.8. <hi>Cant</hi> 5. <hi>Acts</hi> 16.14.<note place="margin">Math. 13.15.</note> But theſe men <hi>ſhut the heart,</hi> dry their tears as <hi>Saul</hi> and ſcalded in their greaſ. The bluſhing once for ſin, hath woaded an impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency in their faces;<note place="margin">Acts 7.</note> and they are as good at reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting the holy Ghoſt, as ever their Fathers were. Other ſome ſuch opportunities God offers ſuch men as theſe, wherein they might advantage the <hi>Church</hi> for ever. Theſe <hi>Potters, &amp;c.</hi> might have gone and helped in the repaire of <hi>Hieruſalem:</hi> the <hi>Phariſees</hi> might have helped forward reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whiles under <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Chriſts</hi> Miniſtry, the Kingdome of God ſuffered violence.</p>
            <p>And now, in theſe active ſtirrings of <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> men (in publique place eſpecially) might put on for the <hi>Churches</hi> reformation; but as the <hi>Potters</hi> were dull, and ſtucke in their dirt, and the <hi>Phariſees</hi> violent in a contrary way: So the moderne <hi>Phariſees</hi> of theſe times are oppoſite, and others, like the <hi>Potters,</hi> are dull. And ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, men at beſt hearken after good newes, yet ſend neither good prayers nor good indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours in their errand to bring them any ſuch tidings: the moſt like <hi>Atalanta,</hi> by ſtouping for the golden balls of the world, ſpend time, and loſe the Goale; they come in a day after the faire, and ſay, <hi>Si putaram,</hi> O if I had thought it would have beene ſo, what would not I have done!</p>
            <p>On the contrary, the ſpirituall liberty-lover is a time obſerver (not ſerver). A time catcher, as <hi>Benhadads</hi> ſervants, catch'd at the King of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> words of mercy.<note place="margin">1 Kings 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.33.</note> Godly men of that temper,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:111902:28"/>of which, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.10. What they have to doe whiles time ſerves, to doe it with all their might, whether for themſelves, or for the <hi>Church:</hi> For themſelves, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> deſcribes the manner to be as conquering in battel;<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.12.</note> 
               <hi>Lay hold of eternall life.</hi> In battel the opportunity muſt be taken; no uſe of after-wit in warre: their hearts catch at opportunities of good, as the eccho catcheth the voyce, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27. For the <hi>Church,</hi> as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and <hi>Ezza,</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul, Gal.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Heſter</hi> tooke the nicke of time.</p>
            <p>And thus you have the ſecond note of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty-loathers ſpirit. Hee is of a negligent ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, of an opportunity loſing ſpirit; hee is the greateſt time-ſerver, but the leaſt time obſerver, hee lookes at the worlds time, not at Gods time,<note place="margin">Pro. 17.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6.</note> the price of wiſedome is put into his hand, but being a foole, hee hath no heart; hee will take none of Gods great penyworth; if hee be invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Chriſts wedding hee will not come;<note place="margin">Math. 22.</note> if a Kingdome or <hi>Church</hi> lie at ſtake, he is wholly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up with his fiddles and his feaſts,<note place="margin">A'mos 6.</note> his fillings and foolings; he doth not for <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State,</hi> or himſelfe, <hi>ſerve his generation,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Act. 13.36.</note> as good men are wont. In all ſuch things hee is an <hi>Epimetheus,</hi> a Poſt-maſter, an after wit:<note place="margin">Pro. 5.11.</note> For evill he <hi>mournes as his later end,</hi> as ſpirituall fooles doe; and for good he hath no mind to doe it,<note place="margin">Pro. 1.28.</note> till hee hath no time to doe it. Hee comes, ſaith <hi>Hierome,</hi> when the gates are ſhut: therefore no peeviſh novell poſition, much unlike to the liberty-lover, that is, a <hi>Prometheus,</hi> a fore-wit, a fore-man, a forward man: For all ſpirituall good for himſelfe, hee
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:111902:29"/>is as a waiter at <hi>Betheſda.</hi> And for the <hi>Church;</hi> how doth he like <hi>Moſes,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 85.8.</note> ſtand in the gap, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent a danger? How doth hee wait as a Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner to expect an anſwer of peace for the <hi>Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> good, rather then to loſe ſpeaking with <hi>God</hi> for the common good,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ 27</note> they will dwell in the houſe of God all the daies of their lives; they will amidſt all thoughts,<note place="margin">Gen 49.18.</note> ſorrowes, ſickneſſe, &amp;c. wait for Gods ſalvation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This liberty-ſlighter is of a ſecure ſpirit: Security is a groundleſſe tranquility in a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous condition; theſe <hi>Potters</hi> and <hi>Planters</hi> ſit and ſing at their worke in <hi>Babylon;</hi> never dreaming of any danger to themſelves or ſoules, now, or for time to come. One would have thought, that the very name <hi>Babylon</hi> (being Hebrew) might have minded them of <hi>confuſion,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen. 11.9.</note> and how it had beene their confuſion by captivating them, and might be their eternall confuſion of ſoule, if they ſhould continue there, when the Church and Ordinances were removed, as now they were removed. And it might be the <hi>Churches</hi> confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſo farre as the want of their helpe might cauſe it by withdrawing or ſtaying behind them in <hi>Babylon:</hi> So then the footing of this third note is broad enough to beare the grounding of generall ſecurity in this mans ſpirit. That this mans ſpirit is carnally ſecure, and feares no dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to the <hi>Church</hi> or his owne ſoule; <hi>Fooles make a mocke of ſinne:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 14 9.</note> and for the generall ſtate, the cry of ſuch men uſually is, <hi>Peace, peace,</hi> and things were never better,<note place="margin">1 Theſſ 5.</note> till ſudden deſtruction be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to come upon them: As the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> ſay,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:111902:29"/>that before a Snow, the ayre will be warmiſh; when the wind lyes, the great raine falls, and the ayre is moſt quiet, when ſuddenly there will be an earthquake. So the nature of ſecurity is to conceive a ſafety in the midſt or approach of danger; like the people of <hi>Laiſh.</hi> And as this is a ſleepy eviil,<note place="margin">Iudg. 18.20.</note> men will ſtrive to ſleepe ſpiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, notwithſtanding the noiſe that is made, that might keep them waking: ſo oft times the Lord in Juſtice, powres on ſuch the ſpirit of a deepe ſleepe.<note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 29.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> When was the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> more ſecure,<note place="margin">Rom. 21.8.</note> then when it was in moſt danger?</p>
            <p>To deſcend as low to particulars, as the Text and Doctrine carries us, wee may note three things in theſe <hi>Potters, &amp;c.</hi> which in all likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood cauſed their carnall ſecurity that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded not the ſpirituall danger of themſelves, or of the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Great Neceſsity.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Worldly goods.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Negative goodneſſe.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Great Neceſsitie,</hi> they were conſtrained by conqueſt in warre at firſt to goe downe into <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> therefore having ſo juſt a call to come thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they thought they were not bound upon and termes to returne.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Wordly goods,</hi> they were not pinch'd in back or belly, they had ſo much of the world, mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, drinke and wages that made their mind to them a Kingdome; yea, that the Kingdome of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> ſeemed to be be their Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Negative goodneſſe,</hi> they are not ſaid to be guilty of notorious vices, or lewdneſſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:111902:30"/>And ſuch morality and civility might make them conceive they need not feare their ſpirituall condition, or any doing amiſſe, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting the <hi>Church:</hi> For one particular great omiſſion is nothing with men that are not guilty of groſſe Commiſſions.</p>
            <p>And thus it is with every carnall ſecure ſpirit, theſe three make them ſecure, both for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and for the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. For themſelves: Firſt, neceſſity at firſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a voluntary impiety at laſt. Say the world, wee are borne in ſinne, wee have all our faults, therefore they take it not to heart, to be uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, unchanged; they thinke they ſhall doe as well as others; wee are all ſinners, ſay they, therefore, as they thinke, we are all alike ſinners, and we ſhall all fare and ſpeed alike; ſo becauſe a man by neceſſity muſt deale with prophane men,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.10.</note> therefore he thinkes he doth not offend, though he be not ſhy of their company when the neceſſary occaſion is ended.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By reaſon of the world a man is made ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure in his own carnall condition; the profits of the world, the not feeling of worldly want, rocks many a man ſpiritually faſt aſleep in a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall condition: the rich man, <hi>Luke</hi> 12. having fulneſſe in his barnes, hath fulneſſe of peace in his heart, that he needed no more to inable him to ſay, <hi>Soule, take thy pleaſure:</hi> when the belly is full, the bones are at reſt. And this is one of the cauſes that the Apoſtle ſaith, not many mighty, not many noble are called.<note place="margin">1 Cor. v. 26.</note> The poore, ſaith our Saviour, are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Goſpelliſed, not
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:111902:30"/>onely receive it, but are changed by it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By reaſon of negative goodneſſe, men are very confident of their ſafe ſpirituall eſtate, though are deeply in a carnall, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.11. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.44. If men omit never ſo much good, ſo as they doe not commit groſſe evill, they thinke their condition ſafe. The hardy man feares not a defect, ſo long as he feeles no paine in his limbs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the <hi>Church,</hi> theſe three alſo doe make the ſecure ſpirited man ſo ſecure, ſo feareleſſe and careleſſe of the common good.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Neceſsity</hi> at firſt, becauſe the <hi>Church</hi> of the <hi>Jewes</hi> had beene captivated to the <hi>Romans</hi> civil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, therefore now they can doe nothing for the truth, but againſt the truth ſpiritually, to the perſecuting of the Apoſtles and crucifying of Chriſt: Though the government of the <hi>Romans</hi> did not intermedle with their Divine Lawes,<note place="margin">Acts 18.15.</note> or Religion. Though in Chriſts time they had the moſt appoſite time of the <hi>Church</hi> reformation, yet they were then moſt oppoſite, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.37. <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.37. they were all againſt the truth. Thus mightily doth a beginning-neceſſity grow to a perpetuity. As the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> tels of a Drunkard that excuſed himſelfe that hee could not chooſe but be drunke, becauſe by cuſtome he had habituated himſelfe to it, it was come to a neceſſity upon him; he thought not on this, that by time hee might unhabite, unneceſſitate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe againe: So becauſe at firſt, till Chriſt ſhould come, there was a neceſſity of Divinely inſtiſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ceremonies, as circumciſion, &amp;c. to point at his comming, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.13. therefore the <hi>Jewes</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:111902:31"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:111902:31"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:111902:32"/>thinke this neceſſity is upon them alwayes when Chriſt is come, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.5. Juſt ſo it is with us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth's time wee were newly come out of thicke darke Popery; and in Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time newly come out of bloody perſecution; ſo that thoſe noble pious Princes had neither opportunity of time, nor ſpace of time to draw an exact platforme of Diſcipline, the times were ſo full of troubles; therefore all the cry is, that if we have juſt no more reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then was in thoſe Princes dayes, we are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly well. Is there not, as wee ſaid before, the infancie of <hi>Churches, Gal.</hi> 4.1. and conſequently the youth and manhood? Muſt ſhe not be clothed with Diſcipline ſutable to her growth, till ſhe come to full manhood, though ſhee grow ſlower then other <hi>Churches;</hi> as <hi>Geneva, Holland, Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Worldly goods,</hi> eaſe, peace, contentments. When is the afflictions of <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſlighted, the troubles of the <hi>Church</hi> diſregarded? When men are at eaſe in <hi>Zion.</hi> Theſe times are for the generall of the ſame complexion: If dangers of warres be over, conſpiracies diſcovered, purſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payments paſt, then they thinke the <hi>Church</hi> is well enough reformed, which is as irrationall as to thinke a man wounded is whole, becauſe hee hath a gay ſuit on.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Negative goodneſſe,</hi> becauſe the conclave of the <hi>Phariſees</hi> were outwardly as painted ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chres, therefore their <hi>Church</hi> needed no more reformation, but oppoſed it, whipped it; they could not be better. Becauſe the Generall of the <hi>Iewiſh Church</hi> then was, as the fooliſh Virgins,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:111902:32"/>Virgins in outward ſhew, though fooliſh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly; therefore 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they ſlumbered. 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they ſlept. Firſt a ſleepe in carnall ſecurity. And becauſe <hi>Samaria</hi> is not at a time ſo bad as <hi>Judah,</hi> therefore <hi>Samaria</hi> conceives her ſelfe to be juſtified, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 16.52. So now adayes, becauſe <hi>England</hi> is not ſo ſuperſtitious as <hi>Rome,</hi> ſo prophane as <hi>Germany,</hi> therefore wee are well enough reformed: as if one ſhould thinke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is not ſicke of the Plague, therefore hee is not ſicke; on the contrary, the ſpirituall li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty-lover cannot truſt himſelfe, or the <hi>Church</hi> upon principles of carnall ſecurity.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Not himſelfe; the principle of <hi>neceſsitie</hi> is with him of no validity. What greater neceſſity is there (as a mans naturall condition is) then in ſin? A man hath brought himſelfe into that conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that he cannot <hi>ceaſe from ſin.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.14.</note> What therefore ſhall he not ſet againſt ſinne? yea, the more he will call for a Chriſt and his Power, to turne his Will: As a man inclining to an hereditary diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, diets himſelfe the more; becauſe Saint <hi>Paul</hi> could not doe the good he would, but the evill he would not, therefore he cries out, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24.</p>
            <p>The principle of <hi>worldly profits</hi> is no pillar to his ſafety. He minds, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30. and he minds that of our Saviour <hi>What ſhall it advantage to win the whole world, and loſe his owne ſoule?</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luke 9.25.</note> Luke 9.25. The much wooll on the the Sheeps backe is oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times his ruine, hee is caught in the thornes, and famiſhed; the fatter the Oxe is, the ſooner hee comes to the ſlaughter.</p>
            <p>The principle of <hi>Negative goodnes</hi> to him, is of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:111902:33"/>no ſatisfaction.<note place="margin">Iames 2.10.</note> Saith he, if <hi>I keepe all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandemens ſave one, and voluntarily live in the breach of one, I am guilty of all.</hi> And I regard but one ſinne, and that but in my heart, God will not heare my prayers.<note place="margin">Pſ 66.18.</note> He cries out of <hi>ſecret evill thoughts,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e 19.</note> of concupiſcence, a wound with an awle,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.</note> inward bleeding will kill.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Not the Church; thoſe carnall principles doth not ſecure the <hi>Church</hi> in his judgement.</p>
            <p>Not that of <hi>neceſsitie,</hi> or conſtraint: For, ſaith he,<note place="margin">Neceſſitas facit ingen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that ſhould more awaken the <hi>Church;</hi> while <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> might voluntarily worke and uſe diligence in labour, they were quiet. But when they were forced with auſtere neceſſity, then they beat the skies with their groanes: whiles things indifferent were left indifferent, the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> was indifferently quiet: But when things indifferent were impoſed as neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, then ſhe began to ſtirre, and not to endure them. To make a thing indifferent to be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, is to take upon on the place of God: and a thing indifferent impoſed upon me as neceſſary, and unavoydable, makes it utterly to loſe the indifferency to me. It is made to mee all one as neceſſary:<note place="margin">Galat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> glories in this, that <hi>Titus</hi> was not <hi>conſtrained</hi> to be circumciſed.</p>
            <p>Nor can <hi>worldly proſperity</hi> aſſure the godly man of the <hi>Churches</hi> felicity. He remembers that the <hi>Church</hi> waxing fat, though called <hi>Jeſurun,</hi> i. e. <hi>The righteous,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32.15.</note> was moſt wilde and wanton, as a fatted pampered Horſe kicks them moſt; that <hi>Iſrael</hi> more tranſgreſſed in <hi>Canaan</hi> then in <hi>Egypt,</hi> or <hi>Babylon,</hi> when the <hi>Church</hi> was in perſecution;
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:111902:33"/>and to flie into the <hi>Wilderneſſe,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Revel. 12.</note> ſhee was clothed with the Sunne; when clothed with Scarled,<note place="margin">Revel 17.</note> ſhe is called an Harlot. Proſperity is a Popiſh note of the <hi>Church;</hi> and I doubt, ſome of thoſe that urge proſperity as a note of a pure Diſcipline, are ſomewhat affected that way:<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Tay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> For (as once a Reverend Paſtor of this Congregation main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in a Sermon here) the <hi>Church</hi> ever loſeth moſt ſpirituality in her proſperity. When the <hi>Chalices</hi> are gold, the <hi>Prieſts</hi> are wooden: In reſt the <hi>Church</hi> contracteth ruſt. How did impiety and error abound, when the Miniſtry of late grew pompous?</p>
            <p>Nor laſtly, can <hi>Negative goodneſſe</hi> be a good ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to the liberty-lover, the ſpiritually ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited man that the <hi>Church</hi> is in a ſafe condition: For <hi>Negative goodneſſe</hi> doth no more but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that a <hi>Church</hi> is not univerſally bad. <hi>Perga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos</hi> had not denyed the faith, <hi>Epheſus</hi> had not fainted, and yet they wanted ſo much good, as that Chriſt ſent Epiſtles or letters from heaven, that hee was highly offended with them, and threatens them, if they repented not. It is the ſame caſe in theſe times, if men plead for many unneceſſary things in the manner of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, that they are negatively good, that is, there is no hurt in them; It is eaſily anſwered, becauſe there is no good in them, they have no place in Gods worſhip. The <hi>Church</hi> is commendable for poſitive good, not for bare abſence of evill.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This liberty-loather, is of a perverted ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, I meane, a more particular pervertedneſſe, by cuſtome: hee is of a cuſtome-pleading ſpirit,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:111902:34"/>from long cuſtom to erre in judgement and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, and to defend it: So theſe <hi>Potters, &amp;c.</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had beene in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and long time had beene <hi>Potters,</hi> therefore they knew not how to take off their ſpirits from that way and to ſet forward towards <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi> So in all ages, men that are carnall, and cannot ſee the excellency of any ſpirituall liberty, are of a time-preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing ſpirit. Tell one of theſe he is a ſinner, why ſo ſaith he are all men, in all ages: tell him of his uſury and unjuſt dealings, of his deceitfull commodities, his unreaſonable prices, hee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers againe, ſo have men done in all ages, in the ſame manner doe all men of my trade deale. So touching the <hi>Church,</hi> tell theſe time-preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers that ſuch things are enormities in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy; preſently they plead antiquity. If we might diſpute ſo, then we might conclude, that Biſhops may, and muſt erre, becauſe ſo many particular Biſhops, and what Councells of Biſhops erred ſoone after 300. yeeres after Chriſt: tell them Miniſters are not regularly and relatively ſet over their congregations, many things are amiſſe in the Lyturgie, the Sabbath day ought not to be ſpent in ſpores. &amp;c. ſtill they oppoſe antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. As <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cha</hi> for his Gods, becauſe Gods, and of ancient <hi>Demetrius</hi> for <hi>Diana,</hi> that come from <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter,</hi> that was of old.</p>
            <p>On the contrary, the ſpirituall Goſpelliſed <hi>libertine</hi>(I doe not ſay <hi>licentious man</hi>) ſees that all theſe pleas to be <hi>paralogiſmes;</hi> fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe arguments, as Saint <hi>James</hi> calls the errings of Hypocrites, <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.12. That by the ſame reaſon theft ſhould
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:111902:34"/>be no ſinne, becauſe it is above ſixteene hundred yeers old ſince a thiefe was crucified with Chriſt. And that this is no inference of any peeviſh ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit onely, heare <hi>Auguſtine</hi> affirme the ſame.<note place="margin">Quaſt. ex veter. Teſt. <hi>114.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Poſſunt etiam latrones, &amp; adulteri pro ſe antiquita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem adferre.</hi> Thieves and adulterers may plead antiquity; but cuſtome not grounded and guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with reaſon, is a corruption, not a cuſtome:<note place="margin">Conſuetudo n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n munita ratione, non eſt conſuctudo ſed cotruptela, <hi>Iuſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nian.</hi> Vetuſt as error is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot veritat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitas, I citul.</note> it is rather to be accounted an antiquity of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, then a countenancing of verity. If bare an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity might goe for verity, then <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alſheka</hi> might juſtifie his ſpeech, that becauſe his Maſters had tyranniſed over Kingdomes and States, and their heathen Gods, that therefore now his Maſter might over the Church, and their true God, <hi>Iſay</hi> 36.18.</p>
            <p>Yea, the true ſpirituall man is ſo farre from pleading ſuch preſcriptions, that himſelfe makes the heavieſt complaints againſt old cuſtomes, if corrupt: As againſt originall ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. Againſt the old tranſgreſſions of the <hi>Church, Ezra</hi> 9.7. The antiquity o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a fault, doth nothing mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigate it, or prevent it's deſerved judgement.<note place="margin">2 Sam. 23.1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> The <hi>Church</hi> in <hi>Davids</hi> time, is puniſhed for a fault committed in <hi>Sauls</hi> time againſt the <hi>Gibeonites;</hi> and who knowes but many of our late evills have beene, becauſe we plead for the corruptions of the <hi>Church;</hi> and becauſe forty yeeres ſince ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſcore of worthy Miniſters were ſuſpended for trifles, to the undoing of them outwardly, and yet this Land never humbled before God for this, nor made ſatisfaction to the perſons. To plead antiquity or cuſtume for a fault, is to aggravate
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:111902:35"/>it, that it is inveterate, it hath reigned to long, it's high time to remove it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Uſe is of reprehenſion; if God will ſo pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the loſers of, and preſcribers againſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>Church-liberty,</hi> how are they to be reproved that cannot indure <hi>Miniſters</hi> in Sermons to plead for this Chriſt-purchaſed liberty? As if their judgements were, that they would ever have the <hi>Church</hi> fettered in ſpirituall ſlavery; they come to <hi>Church,</hi> and if they heare any word let fall, tending to the <hi>Churches</hi> freedome; preſently there they bite their lip, and in the ſtreets the lips of him that ſpake it: They whiſper in the <hi>Church,</hi> and backbite abroad; like thoſe, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 57. 4. that make <hi>a wide mouth againſt God.</hi> And ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch whiſperings againſt the truth, are an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme bad ſigne, and hath divers other bad vices for it's companions, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. <hi>Whiſperers, backbiters, falſe accuſers, haters of God, inventers of evill things.</hi> Drive a Maſtiffe from his carrion, and hee will ſnarle and grin; and ſcare-crowes from the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſſe, and they will make an hideous cry: let <hi>Micha</hi> be robbed of his Idolls, and he will roare, as if his throat were about to be cut. I cloſe the uſe with that, <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.31. <hi>The Prophets propheſie falſly, and the Prieſts beare rule by their meanes, and my people love to have it ſo, and what will yee doe in the end thereof?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. And laſt uſe is for exhortation to particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>Churches</hi> and their viſible memberr; Not to lye ſtill willingly in a ſordid condition of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſlavery, when we may obtaine a God-given liberty; I ſpeake not of licentiouſneſſe, but of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:111902:35"/>liberty; liberty of the ſoule, from ignorance, unregeneratedneſſe, unmortifiedneſſe: of the <hi>Church</hi> from unreformedneſſe; And indeed, theſe goe together. An unreformed <hi>Church</hi> is the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of perſonall ſinfulneſſe. Therfore thruſt we with dint of Divine inforcements to drive you to a due conſideration of the <hi>Churches</hi> liberty.</p>
            <p>See that we want not voyces for the <hi>Church</hi> in <hi>Sodome,</hi> I meane her hemmed about with groſſe impieties, and perſons: ſee there want not a man to ſtand in the gap: ſee what our mindes and ſpirits be; obſerve the ſound of our prayers,<note place="margin">Ier. 5.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> whether wee ſtand for ciphers, or doe give our voyces? or vote contrary to liberty? Obſerve, whether all, <hi>viz.</hi> our mindes, prayer, practices tend to the rooting up, or rooting in the <hi>Garleek, Leeks</hi> and <hi>Onions</hi> of <hi>Egypt?</hi> whether wee love to be <hi>Potters,</hi> ye, <hi>Porters, Brick-makers,</hi> yea, <hi>Bricke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layers</hi> to build new <hi>Babel,</hi> or elſe are wee thoſe that would by prayer, and lawfull practice pull it downe? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137.</p>
            <p>To put us and preſſe us the right way, we will lay downe <hi>Motives</hi> and <hi>Meanes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Motives</hi> to put us on to make out after the <hi>Churches</hi> ſpirituall liberty are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. God will <hi>record:</hi> this implies Gods taking an account of the number of oppoſites to liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, both ſo farre as they provoke God, and ſo farre as God intends to puniſh them, yea, and lookes frowningly on the <hi>Church,</hi> that hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ſuch to abound, hath educated her viſible
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:111902:36"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:111902:36"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:111902:37"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:111902:37"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:111902:38"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:111902:38"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:111902:39"/>members no better, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.20. And truely great is the number now of men of contrary mindes: As in <hi>Egypt,</hi> when the <hi>Flies</hi> and <hi>Frogs</hi> ſwarmed, and multiplied, they were a judgement; ſo in theſe times, the vermin of the Church lighting and croking every where; perſwading or ſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every where, are a ſad <hi>omen,</hi> an ill Prognoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of deliverance; and eſpecially becauſe, as thoſe vermin keepe together: ſo the enemies of reformation ſwarme and buzze, and croke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. <hi>A kingdome divided againſt it ſelfe cannot ſtand:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat 12.25.</note> an Army in a mutinie cannot oppoſe a common adverſary; were are weakened this day to ſeeke a reformation, our cryes are mixt with contraries. As at the 2. Temple ſome cryed, and ſome ſhouted; and for the wickedneſſe of the great oppoſite number, and for the fewneſſe and coldneſſe of us of another minde, a want of voyces, or vigor in our praying votes, the Lord may juſtly leave the yoke upon us, if we doe not beſtirre us. Doe the birds of prey crow and whule about their carrion? then let the birds of ſong ſit in the wood,<note place="margin">Can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>the wilderneſſe</hi> of the world, and hold up our beaks, our mouthes to heaven, and ſound out a loud our devotions to heaven, and never leave till an eccho,<note place="margin">P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 85.8.</note> an anſwer of peace be returned. Out cry the murmurings of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe minded. 'Tis true, the ſinne of <hi>Sodome</hi> cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed loudly, and loudly to heaven, ſo that God came downe to hearken to the cry. But had there beene but a voyce or two more of Saints, their prayers had out-cried them; a few birds
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:111902:39"/>of ſong are ſhriller then many crocitating birds of prey. Up and be doing, the thing ſtill is feiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; though many are oppoſite. The time is not long ſince, wherein the prayers and faſtings of a few particular family-meetings, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, prevailed more on the one ſide for the peace of the Church, then a Land of ſecure ones, and an army of ſouldiers in the field, on the contrary, to plunge it in blood.</p>
            <p>So then the energie or ſinne of the <hi>Motive</hi> is, that we ſo beſtirre our ſelves, and ſo multiply our prayers and ſupplications, above our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that when God comes to record, hee may finde more cryes on our ſide then on theirs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Motive,</hi> God records with <hi>diſgrace</hi> thoſe that decline, or any way neglect their ſpirituall liberty. What a brand is left upon <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that they ſo oft returned into <hi>Egypt</hi> in their hearts? VVhat a brand is left upon ten of the ſpies, for diſheartening the people from going up to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan?</hi> What a brand upon theſe <hi>Potters</hi> for not returning? How are wee aſhamed of our names in the Books of Martyrs, if the perſons belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thoſe names were Popiſh, and helpers for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of the Churches bondage? How in later times have wee ſeene, when our <hi>Parliament</hi> men were choſen, the names of <hi>Gentlemen</hi> that loved their Countries bondage, torne with the teeth of the multitude, ſhaken as Dog or Swine will a rotten clout? They were caſt aſide as a pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheard, huffed and puffed away as chaffe, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectors rejected: So for thoſe Miniſters thad had
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:111902:40"/>beene innovators, cringers and bowers to names and tables, or old ſuperſtitious Ceremony-mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, how are they caſt off as an old naſty ſuit, as the object of all mens ſcorne? yea, all yeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, tradeſmen, and freemen whatſoeever, that have contended in the behalfe of men of men unfit for publike place in Parliament or Pulpit, that would willing by have ſet over us hard taske-maſters if they could, how are they the <hi>by-word</hi> of all ingenious men. And be ſure of it theſe times and paſſages will be recorded in future ages; for never any age afforded more matter for hiſtory then theſe times, I ſay they <hi>will</hi> be recorded, if they be not already. I have heard of an hiſtory of theſe times printed in <hi>France:</hi> but be ſure we ſhall in after times have it in plaine <hi>Engliſh,</hi> there by divine providence ſhall all be ſet downe, if men carry themſelves unevenly: as ſuppoſe that ſuch men did ſo much, were at ſo great coſt in going againſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant <hi>Scots,</hi> that in concluſion carryed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo innocently: but did nothing againſt the Popiſh <hi>Iriſh,</hi> that in the very beginning exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſuch bloody cruelties: that ſuch Gentlemen hindred the reformation, which the Parliament would have effected, had not they beene oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite; that ſuch Miniſters ſtill preached, plotted, petitioned that they might were the yoke of bondage. I make but a <hi>ſuppoſition,</hi> with <hi>Ifs</hi> &amp; <hi>Ands,</hi> what may be ſtoried of us. But you may happly imagine. that <hi>poſitively</hi> groſſe men ſhall be more groſſely ſet forth to all future ages, never to be forgotten to the worlds end. If therefore you
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:111902:40"/>have any true blood running in your veines if any eſteeme of your reputation before God and the world, ſhew your ſelves worthy men in the behalfe of the Churches liberty and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous tranquility.</p>
            <p>You ſee the force of the <hi>Motive</hi> is, that God and men ſhall conſpire to blot your names with reproach to the worlds end, if you doe not write your names faire with noble actions, and write over them this Motto, <hi>I will doe what I can for God and his Church,</hi> then will God prevent, and men forbeare to mention you but for honour. How did God and <hi>Moſes</hi> heale the reproach of <hi>Levi</hi> in matter of the <hi>Sechemites,</hi> when after, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on command of publike authority they ſtood up for God againſt the Idolaters?</p>
            <p>Theſe times are full of eyes, every man is an <hi>Argos;</hi> Be you full of hands, a <hi>Briareus</hi> for God, and the Church, and the <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> ſhall not leave out a title of your honour, yee never had ſuch a time, or ſhall have to be graced or diſgraced in your name, as this is.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Mot.</hi> God will <hi>diſcard,</hi> caſt off ſuch, he leaves them to loſe themſelves, by loſing the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of time. Theſe <hi>Potters</hi> loſing this op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, never returned that we reade of. The deſigne was infinitely too great for them to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake alone: <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> loſing her day, all other dayes were hid from her eyes, and her houſe was left deſolate, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. <hi>Luke</hi> 19.</p>
            <p>So now is an unparalelled time for us. Three Kingdomes awakened and their Parliaments.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:111902:41"/>Now let us joyne purſes, prayers, powers, petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, practices, and great things may be done.</p>
            <p>Loſe wee this opportunity, and wee ſhall in all humane probabilitie, never ſee the like againe, becauſe now in all Kingdomes, <hi>God hath</hi> (it ſeemes by their common vote) <hi>put it into their hearts to hate the whore of</hi> Babylon.<note place="margin">Rev. 17 16.</note> And powerfull is the generall conſent and vote of the people to move forward any good worke;<note place="margin">Rev. 19.6.</note> their very voyce is as the ſound of many waters: and how prevailing is a flood or river of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? Now wee may goe on in good with the ſtreame; in ſome degree omit this opportunity, and after we muſt goe againſt the ſtreame. Now pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ltion may doe that, which after the point of the ſword cannot, as it ought not. Now may be bought with words and teares, which after cannot be blood and ſpeares.</p>
            <p>Yea, loſe we the opportunity but for a piece of our redreſſes, and it cannot be well with us. Have wee not a propriety in our goods? then our eſtates are gone. Have we not deliverance from oppreſſing Courts? then our perſons or bodies are loſt. Have wee not a right ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a right miniſtrie? then our ſoules are undone.</p>
            <p>So that the maine <hi>point</hi> of this motive is, <hi>punctum temporis, Articulus temporis,</hi> this is the point of time, that may ſettle all in joynt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Motive,</hi> God will caſt us off, if we ſlight ſuch offers and times of offers, as <hi>graceleſſe;</hi> caſt us off from the meanes of grace, or the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:111902:41"/>meanes from them, and give them up to the cruelty of men. If wee be ſluggiſh to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing, if not damning of our children, wee ſhall loſe the meanes of grace and ſo grace. If wee ſecretly <hi>preſcribe</hi> (for in our hearts wee dote upon the continuance of corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the Church) God will <hi>preſcribe</hi> openly. If wee by ſluggiſhneſſe in the forefront leade our poſterity for future into captivity, wee ſhall goe firſt into captivitie.</p>
            <p>Remember the rule;<note place="margin">Amos 6.</note> Our enemies <hi>love the treaſon againſt the Church, not the traytors;</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member how they ſerved <hi>Cranmer,</hi> after hee had recanted, they burnt him whiles hee was in a good minde to ſerve their turne. And note how the <hi>Prelates</hi> among themſelves ſerved the great <hi>Antiſcibbatarian</hi> Prelate, when he had ſerved their turnes, hee was much caſt off by them, as I gathered from one his of owne ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; haply, becauſe he held not Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation too. <hi>Fides non eſt ſervanda cum Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticis.</hi> 'Tis burning, not turning that they aime at in eminent profeſſors.</p>
            <p>See the ſumme of this Motive: If we make God caſt us off, wee loſe his Grace, and all favour of men. It is not Religion onely, but our lives alſo, that wee ſhall loſe; No merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ruine like to that which ariſeth out of contrariety of Religion.</p>
            <q>Tantum Religio potuit ſuadere molorum.</q>
            <p n="5">5. Liberty-loſers ſaith the <hi>Doct.</hi> are men of unworthy, unready ſpirits. Shall we be unready
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:111902:42"/>for our owne good? Not rightly informed in judgement; not ready in affections to practiſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on opportunities? Not ready in affections, as not ſenſible of the miſery of ſpirituall bondage? Not ready in judgement, as not enlightened touching the excellency of Chriſts reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Church? unprepared in prayers, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings, &amp;c? Yea, unfit in prayer, and unfit in perſon? For God muſt prepare the heart, as well as to receive the thing petitioned for; as to make the prayer.<note place="margin">Pſ. 10.17.</note> There were ſome fitted in prayer, as we may ſay, but not fitted in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.3.4. Forget not this, that refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation goes on when the heart is prepared, eſpecially in publique perſons:<note place="margin">2 Chron. 27.6.</note> So in <hi>Jothams</hi> time;<note place="margin">2 Chron. 29.36.</note> ſo in <hi>Hezechiahs</hi> time.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Who</hi> preferre, <hi>Who</hi> are they? Peaſants for the moſt; Their <hi>ſtocke</hi> was diſſembling, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting Polititians, <hi>Deputies, Judges</hi> in <hi>Moab,</hi> men of the <hi>Lye.</hi> And the <hi>ſtalke,</hi> the men them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Dike</hi> in a Sermon on 1 Ioh. 5.</note> Planters, Hedgers, &amp;c. One in a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon called them Hedge-rogues. And ſure un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch termes doth God ſet forth ſuch Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants ſpirits, deſpiſing ſpiritualls, <hi>Job</hi> 30.7. They bray under the buſhes, and under the nets, they gather together, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Moab ſhall be as So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> how is that? <hi>The breeding of nettles and ſalt pits.</hi> For <hi>Sodome</hi> deſpiſed <hi>Lots</hi> Miniſtery, and became a deſolation, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.23. <hi>Goe yee into the high wayes and hedges;</hi> the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> yet ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in bondage are ſuppoſed to lye under hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, as it were, that is, men deſpicable.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:111902:42"/>
            <p>And obſerve all along the courſe of times, men baſe or meane in the ſtock, being ſuddenly advanced become in their ſpirits (and that is worſt of all) moſt baſe and unworthy in the <hi>ſtalke;</hi> they prove <hi>Daubers</hi> with <hi>untempered mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Ezech.</hi> 13.10. <hi>Planters,</hi> but envious <hi>ones, ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Tares, Matth.</hi> 13.25. <hi>Hedgers,</hi> but not to <hi>hedge in,</hi> as <hi>Hoſ</hi> 2. but hedge out the Church; ſuch as throw thornes into the Churches way. So that ſhe had need be fenced with <hi>ſhooes,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeakes; yea, <hi>iron,</hi> as the Prophet ſpeakes.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.</note> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member for a preſident, Cardinall <hi>Woolſey,</hi> and many ſince that, <hi>ejuſdem farinae,</hi> of the ſame branne.</p>
            <p>Obſerve whether the Motive drives; that to be baſe in ſpirit, accuſeth of baſeneſſe in ſtocke: or if not in ſtocke, yet in ſtalke, which ſhall be a ſtocke to a future breed, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, And oft times God caſteth blemiſhes of nature upon men notoriouſly peccant. One obſerved, that in his time all <hi>Arminians</hi> had a blemiſh in one of their eyes. Another obſerved, that one turning with the times, beginning to bow towards Altars, never went upright more. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vendum eſt ab eo quem naturae notavit,</hi> ſay the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turaliſts,</hi> Men in common experience, are mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for exceeding good, or extreme bad.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Mot.</hi> preferre a ſordid condition; in body to be <hi>Potters;</hi> in ſtate to be in compariſon poore; in freedome of perſon liable to <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire and taxes; in life liable to be preſſed to the <hi>Heathen</hi> Kings warres, to fight for <hi>Babylon;</hi> yea,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:111902:43"/>and, perhaps, againſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> this is a type of us of our times; in crying up the corrupt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and things of the times: <hi>Babylon</hi> is a type of <hi>Rome, Romes</hi> Religion is partly Heatheniſh: So <hi>Moriſinus</hi> in a Treatiſe. <hi>Romes</hi> ſlaverie as bad or worſe then <hi>Babylon;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rev. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> they are neerer to us, even partly amongſt us. If ever wee be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaved, it is to <hi>Rome;</hi> wee have felt it oft and oft in former ages. And when caſt off the yoke once or twice, ſtill they indeavour to caſt it on, like <hi>Vulcans</hi> net, inviſible; or like the great <hi>Turkes</hi> golden fetters. If wee fall into ſlavery to them, our bodies muſt be inſlaved, we muſt have their marke in the hand, as well as in the forehead; we muſt worke for them, as well as diſpute; our eſtates muſt be ſubject to them: See in Hiſtories what pollings the <hi>Pope</hi> exerciſed upon all mens purſes. B. <hi>Bonner</hi> ſaid, that the <hi>Pope</hi> had more out of <hi>England</hi> then the crowne; our ſoules muſt be ſubject: For the <hi>Pope</hi> deales in ſoules; wee muſt believe as they believe to our perdition.</p>
            <p>See then, preferre, ſpeake for the corruptions of the times, and it is a ſtirrup for <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> to get up on our backs, and ride us for Aſſes.</p>
            <p n="8">8. And laſt <hi>Motive</hi> is, that if wee refuſe, wee refuſe <hi>a God-given liberty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Spirituall liberty, Goſpel liberty, more freely to doe good,<note place="margin">Iob. 24.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Pſalmes 119.68.</note> makes us <hi>like God,</hi> the freeſt agent, and the fulleſt of doing of good; when a man is a ſlave, or but a ſervant, hee cannot doe good, what, where, and when he would: So ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually, when ſubject to humane inventions and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:111902:43"/>ceremonious nets of men; but when the Sunne hath made us free, like Chriſt wee are free in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, to goe about doing all good, at all conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient times.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. <hi>penul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It is purchaſed by <hi>God-Chriſt:</hi> for by Chriſt is redemption; and if every thing that is for freedome, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 4.18. <hi>Luke</hi> 1. <hi>Luke</hi> 4.18. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.12.</p>
            <p n="3">3. God hath given us ſome pledges of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ſpirituall liberties hoped for in theſe times. It is a wiſe <hi>decorum,</hi> that when Bills of piety are to be ſigned, bills of profit ſhould be ſealed. An Act for ſubſidies is ſubſidiary, to put forward a Bill for ſanctity: The Act of pol-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, to the acts to puſh downe oppreſſing Courts; but the maine Bill for the Churches libertie is yet behinde; if that come laſt and alone, that it may not be loſt, we muſt joyne with it ſubſidy-prayers, pole-prayers, every one muſt pay a pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of prayer. The acts for God ſhould be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with that which is moſt agreeable to God; and that is prayer. <hi>Niniveh</hi> in their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe paid by pole, I meane, prayed by pole for their deliverance; men; women and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and beaſts after their kinde, cried out for deliverance, much more ſhould this be done in a Chriſtian Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="2">2. meanes
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Remove,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Move.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Remove thoſe things that hinder theſe Potters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Move thoſe things that may helpe you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Remove:</hi> 1. They might thinke, that it was but arbitrary whether they returned, not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:111902:44"/>Know wee, it is an injunction, not a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to ſue out our liberty, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.1.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Long continuance of their travell in an heatheniſh land did much marre them: So tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling into <hi>Italy</hi> and Popiſh Countries doe much marre our Gentry from doing the Church that ſervice in ſuing out her liberty. Pity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore but there were a Statute againſt ſuch tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels; however there is a Divine ſtatute, <hi>Come out from among them,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> doth not imply goe in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them that are uncleane. Men of place muſt forget to alledge how much worſe other places, and ſee how much worſe wee be then the rule.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They loved the King of <hi>Babylon,</hi> yet did not love the man, becauſe an heathen. In <hi>Iudea</hi> they had juſt cauſe to love the King and the man both, becauſe religious: Let men beware of that <hi>Alexander</hi> the King ſaid to his attendants: many of you, ſaith he, love <hi>Alexander,</hi> but doe not love the King. Men that will reforme, muſt love as well him the Chriſtian, as him the <hi>King.</hi> The man as well as the Magiſtrate, muſt ſeeke the good as well as the greatneſſe of the higher Peers and powers. If reformers admire onely greatneſſe, they will only comply to pleaſe men. But, if as Chriſtians they love their King and Country as Chriſtians, they will petition and practiſe for ſuch a reformation as may pleaſe God, and bring inward joy and outward glory to King and kingdome; they will ſo Chriſtian-like ſpeake to a Chriſtian King, that <hi>Agnoſcat ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiat<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:111902:44"/>ſibi non principi dici,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Plin. <hi>2.</hi> Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. ad Trajan.</note> That they wiſh <hi>him</hi> well, and not flatter <hi>greatneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. They did not reckon time as thoſe that went up did, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.2. let <hi>Daniel</hi> reckon for us too. <hi>cap.</hi> 12.11. The abomination was in <hi>Julians</hi> time, 360. then <hi>Julian</hi> would ſet up the Temple againe in deſpight of the Chriſtians,<note place="margin">Bright. Sym. G.</note> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſet up the Jewiſh <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this time of 360. adde 1290. and there is made juſt 1650. And it is 1641. already, yea, drawing 1642. Now therefore in all probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity is the high time for the worke to be on foot for all Chriſtendome, and I hope <hi>Ireland</hi> will be the laſt publike reſiſtance againſt refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</p>
            <p n="5">5. They did not deeme this the onely oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity; this is ours onely, A Parliament like to continue, The <hi>Iriſh</hi> tugging for a blood-ſhedding <hi>Religion;</hi> therefore wee for a blood-ſaving <hi>Religion,</hi> but not in their way: wee by petition and Parliament, not by ſword and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion. The dumbe daughter of <hi>Creſus</hi> could ſpeake when one was about to kill her father, ſaying, Will yee kill <hi>Creſus?</hi> Who would not ſpeake for the Church, and againſt Popery, when it is about to kill our mother, the Church? <hi>Poſteſt occaſio calva,</hi> The Church, I am ſure will be bald, if wee catch not hold on Chriſt, who waits our reformation till his locks be wet, yea, with blood and teares of his Saints, <hi>And God will wound the hairy ſcalpe of him that goes on in his iniquity to hinder the Churches returning to
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:111902:45"/>liberty,</hi> Pſal. 68.21. compared with <hi>verſe</hi> 22. Now, the King and all Iſrael is met to bring in the Arke, therefore let the Prieſt and people goe on with ſupplications and acclamations.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Move on thoſe indeavours, and put on thoſe perſons that will beſt advantage the cauſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let every man as he is ſet in the orbe of the Church, do that which is in his power. <hi>The ſtars</hi> (though of ſeverall magnitudes) <hi>fought in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der againſt Siſera,</hi> the enemy of the Church: the ſonne of <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> perſwaded his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 5.</note> the mother perſwaded the father, and the father ruled the City: the Prophet ſpake to the Queene, the Queene to the King, and ſo <hi>Adonijahs</hi> diſobedience was ſuppreſſed;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cai</hi> ſpeaks to <hi>Heſter</hi> the Queen, <hi>Heſter</hi> to the King <hi>Ahaſhuerus,</hi> and ſo conſpiracies were preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Every man muſt improve that, or ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>talents</hi> of power,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.</note> prayer and purſe, that God hath put into his hands, in a regular way to put forward the Churches reformation, till it come to perfection.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider what are leading Caſes &amp; Cauſes. And every one in his order, and to his power regularly to put on ſuch. <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and <hi>Ezra</hi> firſt built the walls, ſecondly, oppoſe <hi>Sanballat</hi> and <hi>Tobiah:</hi> thirdly, built the Temple, and ſet up it's ſervices. Regular reformation firſt ſets the State or Common-wealth, the walls of the Church in good repaire; ſecondly, oppoſeth thoſe that conſpire againſt the Church and her
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:111902:45"/>Chriſtian Sabbaths. Removes the men that have got into their hands the Monopolies of the Churches miſery; ſuch being removed, the miſery they bring is removed: when the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of trees fall, the ſprigs fall and breake: thirdly, ſets up the pure worſhip of Chriſt for matter and forme; Chriſts Doctrine and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, which ſet up, beare all manner of good fruit.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Meanes:</hi> Of Cauſes or Caſes of an equall conſequence, put on that which will firſt goe; the good workeman drives that naile that will firſt goe; till hee hath well faſtened his worke: ſo ſpiritually,<note place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>za 9.8.</note> * when an Architect hath ſet up divers bayes of building;<note place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c 12.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> or ſeverall poſts and beames; there falls out divers little roomes for cupboards or cloſets, or, &amp;c. that could not be ſo well foreſeene. In mechanick arts oft times one piece occaſioneth another; be alwayes do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, building of the <hi>Church,</hi> according as God hath made you <hi>Beſaleels,</hi> or <hi>Aholiabs,</hi> or <hi>Moſeſes,</hi> and <hi>Aarons,</hi> or, &amp;c. And after a while you ſhall ſee your way better to goe on; and at laſt God will give you an eternall habitation in the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens: and even ſo be it to all that love <hi>Sion, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
